<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>CWB Writing</title>
  <subtitle>The Works of Christopher Buecheler</subtitle>
  <link href="https://cwbwriting.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://cwbwriting.com/"/>
  <updated>2026-01-13T17:24:14Z</updated>
  <id>https://cwbwriting.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name>Christopher Buecheler</name>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  
  <entry>
    <title>CWB Writing Newsletter - January 2026 | Post | CWB Writing</title>
    <link href="https://cwbwriting.com/posts/2026-01-cwb-writing-newsletter-january-2026/"/>
    <updated>2026-01-13T17:24:14Z</updated>
    <id>https://cwbwriting.com/posts/2026-01-cwb-writing-newsletter-january-2026/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s 2026!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seems impossible, the relentless march of time, and yet here we are again in a brand new year. Let&#39;s talk about writing stuff! I&#39;ve got two updates: Possessed, and the third book in my Ageless Queen series (the first of which, &lt;a href=&quot;https://cwbwriting.com/books/#pietytheknife&quot;&gt;Piety the Knife&lt;/a&gt;, we&#39;ve talked about quite a bit in the past).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Possessed&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As mentioned in my last email, I&#39;m self-publishing my contemporary fantasy, Possessed, this year. It&#39;s a fun book that I think fans of my vampire titles will really enjoy. It&#39;s not quite as dark and gritty as those, but it&#39;s got the same blend of interesting characters, modern-day fantasy, and catchy dialog. It&#39;s also really funny, if I say so myself (which I feel comfortable doing because multiple other people have also said so)!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hired a freelance editor to give it a read and get back to me with thoughts on where the book needs work before publication. The good news is: they thought it was very strong in its current state, so the areas for improvement are mostly tweaks around the edges, not stuff at its core that needs serious rewrites. This is good for two reasons. First, it means less work for me (woo!). Second, it means faster delivery for you. I don&#39;t have a release date yet, but I&#39;m more confident about getting it out in the first half of 2026 now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what are the next steps? Well, first I&#39;ll put together a plan to address the feedback. Then I&#39;ll write the bits and bobs I need to do so, and get them fit seamlessly into the book. Once that&#39;s done (and I plan to start this month), I&#39;ll spend some time copyediting – just searching for typos and that kind of thing. Once I have a finished, clean draft, I&#39;ll begin assembling the eBook. That&#39;ll take like two hours. Then I&#39;ll begin assembling the print edition. That&#39;ll take several days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to do either of those assemblies, I&#39;ll need a cover. So, starting in a few weeks, I&#39;ll be engaging in a search for an illustrator. I&#39;ll have a whole post about it over on my writing site, which I&#39;ll be promoting on &lt;a href=&quot;https://bsky.app/profile/cwbuecheler.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;BlueSky&lt;/a&gt; and on various artist-focused sites. The goal is to find a talented pro whose style is a good fit for the story. Once I have the illustration, I&#39;ll turn it into a cover.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ll be updating a lot more once I have a clear idea of when exactly Possessed is coming out. I&#39;d like to get it into people&#39;s hands ahead of summer, as I think it&#39;s a &lt;em&gt;great&lt;/em&gt; beach read. We&#39;ll see!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Ageless Queen&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As mentioned in the last email, the plan was to spend November and December writing the third book in the series I&#39;m currently calling &lt;em&gt;The Ageless Queen&lt;/em&gt;. The first book, Piety the Knife, is the one that landed me my second literary agent. We&#39;re still holding off on sending that one out to publishers right now, but hopefully the market will swing back toward epic/dark fantasy soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, I want to finish this series whether or not we ever manage to sell it, so I did what I said I&#39;d do! Over the course of forty-two days, I wrote 93,781 words, which is about 385-390 print pages. A nice, good-sized, but not overwhelmingly long book. About the same length as my novel &lt;a href=&quot;https://cwbwriting.com/books/#thebrokengodmachine&quot;&gt;The Broken God Machine&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The entire book is a prequel, in a sense. It takes place many, many years before the first two books in the series, and answers a lot of the questions that readers will have about the world of the Ageless Queen. I think it&#39;s pretty good. Needs work, of course … but all first drafts do. It&#39;s currently in the hands of my advance readers (including my brilliant wife Charlotte, who&#39;s already finished it). My agent Diana and her assistant are also taking a look at it. Once I have their feedback, I&#39;ll sit on it for a bit and let it kick around in my brain, and then I&#39;ll get to work on a new draft!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Wrap-up&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think 2026 is going to be a big year for my writing, and I&#39;m looking forward to working on both of the above projects, and more, this year. Also really excited to finally get a new book into your hands. I think you&#39;re really going to like this one. Stay tuned for more!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hope you have a great new year,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;-Chris&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;You can get these updates before they hit the blog by subscribing to the newsletter!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>CWB Writing Newsletter - November 2025 | Post | CWB Writing</title>
    <link href="https://cwbwriting.com/posts/2025-12-cwb-writing-newsletter-november-2025/"/>
    <updated>2025-12-13T14:19:35Z</updated>
    <id>https://cwbwriting.com/posts/2025-12-cwb-writing-newsletter-november-2025/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Well hello there!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s been a long time since I sent out one of these newsletters. There are reasons for that, and I&#39;ll get to them shortly, but I hope you&#39;re all doing great and are ready for some good news! We&#39;ve got three things to talk about: &lt;strong&gt;Piety the Knife&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Possessed&lt;/strong&gt;, and a &lt;strong&gt;new book&lt;/strong&gt;. Let&#39;s jump in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those who need a refresher, I landed my second literary agent, Diana Fox, with my dark fantasy novel &lt;a href=&quot;https://cwbwriting.com/books/#pietytheknife&quot;&gt;Piety the Knife&lt;/a&gt;. We&#39;ve been working on that book for a while. Took longer than we&#39;d hoped due to a combination of factors, including 2024 being an absolutely hellish year for her.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the interim, I wrote the sequel and laid out plans for finishing the series. I also moved to France permanently which was … a lot. The time flew, and I barely did any writing for a while there. I&#39;m firmly established in Paris, now, and ready to dive back in to writing. In fact, I already have!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Piety is on hold. It&#39;s basically ready to go, but we&#39;re not shopping it to publishing houses right now. Why? Because dark fantasy goes in cycles and right now editors aren&#39;t buying it. Diana loves the book and wants to give it the best shot she can at getting published, so we&#39;re holding off and seeing how things look in the new year (and maybe beyond).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s frustrating, but I&#39;d far rather wait than just send it to a bunch of editors and get a bunch of &amp;quot;loved it, not going to buy it&amp;quot; responses! We&#39;ve no doubt Dark/Epic Fantasy will come back around. It&#39;s an evergreen genre that always gains new fans. It&#39;s just a matter of timing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To keep myself busy, I decided on two projects: the first is that &lt;strong&gt;I&#39;m going to self-publish my contemporary fantasy &lt;a href=&quot;https://cwbwriting.com/books/#possessed&quot;&gt;Possessed&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;! I&#39;ve been talking about doing that for some time, but what makes &lt;em&gt;this time&lt;/em&gt; different, is that I&#39;ve already engaged an editor and paid her to begin working on the book. Putting my money where my mouth is, so to speak. I don&#39;t have a release date for Possessed yet, but it&#39;ll be sometime in 2026, probably the first half. I&#39;ll have more information on the book and its release soon! For now, please enjoy this snippet:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
“But I thought demons had names. Matthias is always going on about them. Beelzebub and Corson and all them.”
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
“Those names mean nothing to me. How are you not getting this? Is this how Hindu people feel when some well-meaning idiot asks them how they celebrate Christmas?”
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
“I get it. You’re not Christian.”
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
“I don’t know that those other demons, if they even exist, would call themselves Christian either, but—”
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
“Fine. So what should I call you?”
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
“I don’t know.” The demon seemed to think about it for a second. “Just try to think of something cool.”
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
“I’m going to call you Matt Demon.”
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Another pause. “Try &lt;em&gt;much harder&lt;/em&gt; to think of something cool.”
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
“Too late!” Amber laughed. “Shoulda come up with your own name. You are totally Matt Demon now.”
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
“Don’t make me crash this car.”
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Could he do that? Amber didn’t think he could. Not if she fought him. It was one thing to move her head or threaten to walk to the bathroom without her permission. It was another thing to try to kill her.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
“You’re not crashing anything,” she said. “Maybe if you stop being such an asshole, I’ll think of something else to call you.”
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
No response to that, so Amber drove for a while in silence. She was about five minutes out from Dylan’s house when the demon spoke again. “I think this banishment spell might be the best thing for both of us.”
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other project I&#39;m working on is the third book in the Piety series. Yes, it&#39;s a little weird to move on to &lt;em&gt;another&lt;/em&gt; sequel when we&#39;re not even sure if the first two books will ever sell … but it&#39;s what I want to write. This series is, in my opinion, the very best stuff I&#39;ve ever written. I&#39;m going to finish it, whether or not it ever gets traditionally published. This third book will either by the next in a four-volume series, or parts of it will make it into the final book if we decide to go for a trilogy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started the first draft on November first and, as always, will be writing on it seven days a week until it&#39;s done. I&#39;m currently averaging just over 2,000 words per day, which is great! The book tells the story of a curse long-established by the time Piety and his friends make it onto the scene, and provides a lot of historical background for the world I&#39;ve built that I think people will really enjoy. It also sets up a lot of well-used princess tropes and then smashes them all to pieces!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that I&#39;m up and moving again with my writing, this newsletter will resume its bi-monthly updates. So I&#39;ll see you all in the new year with more news!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;-Chris&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;You can get these updates before they hit the blog by subscribing to the newsletter!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Let&#39;s Talk about Silksong | Post | CWB Writing</title>
    <link href="https://cwbwriting.com/posts/2025-10-silksong/"/>
    <updated>2025-10-22T07:05:27Z</updated>
    <id>https://cwbwriting.com/posts/2025-10-silksong/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;div style=&quot;width: 100%; max-width: 1200px; margin: 0 auto 1rem auto; font-size: 11px; color: #666; line-height: 1;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://cwbwriting.com/_img/silksong/silksong1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Silksong Screenshot - Hornet sits on a bench with Sherma standing nearby&quot; style=&quot;width: 100%; margin: 0 0 2px 0; padding: 0;&quot; /&gt;credit: &lt;a href=&quot;https://steamcommunity.com/id/flashmallow/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;flash&lt;/a&gt; on Steam&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Warning: There are significant spoilers for this game throughout this post. If you haven&#39;t finished it yet, I would bail.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So …&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s been a month and change since Hollow Knight: Silksong was released, and in that time there&#39;s been a lot of discussion about the game and its challenges. I bought it on day one, played through the entire thing, 100%-ed it, and then went back and played Hollow Knight to 107% (I skipped colo 3 and the pantheons because I don&#39;t like them). I have thoughts. Let&#39;s get to them!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First off, let me preface this by saying that, barring something truly amazing happening in the next couple of months, Silksong is my game of the year. It is a &lt;em&gt;marvelous&lt;/em&gt; game, beautifully crafted with tremendous intent and attention to detail. It is bigger and more ambitious than Hollow Knight, tells a deeper story, and allows for even more player agency in terms of build setup and approach to combat. Movement is faster, more varied, and more intuitive than in Hollow Knight. The game features some of the most stunningly-crafted visuals ever in a 2D platformer / Metroidvania, has an insane level of attention to detail that you just don&#39;t see in most titles, and the music—a thing I rarely notice in games, even those whose music gets a ton of love—is spectacular.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, &lt;strong&gt;Hollow Knight is a better game&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Team Cherry made three missteps with Silksong that ultimately I think cause it to crumble just slightly under its own weight. Difficulty is not one of them. Is the game hard? Yes. But not that hard, not really. It&#39;s all just pattern recognition for bosses and some manual dexterity stuff for platforming. If you&#39;re planning to tell me to &amp;quot;git gud&amp;quot; or whatever, I&#39;m already gud. I&#39;m not a god-tier gamer but I&#39;m quite good at games like this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s talk about the things I believe are issues:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;It&#39;s Too Long&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus Christ, this game is long. Sure, I play these games cautiously and slowly. I read every dialog, I talk to &lt;em&gt;everyone&lt;/em&gt; repeatedly to make sure I haven&#39;t missed anything, and I focus on exploring and making sure I&#39;ve checked every corner of every area. It took me about eighty-four in-game hours to reach 100%. My first playthrough of Hollow Knight, in which I achieved the true ending and had over 100% completion, was less than half that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As good as the game is, I was pretty ready for it to be done at about forty hours. I was &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; ready for it to be done at sixty hours. At eighty hours, it was basically a grim death march of just doing things for the sake of getting to the end. Could I have skipped some of those things? Yes! But I didn&#39;t know which would be fun or interesting, and which wouldn&#39;t, so I felt like I needed to do them all. The endgame, especially, is a slog but little of its content is really optional. Once you trigger Act Three, you&#39;re in the shit, and the only way out is through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you just do the two acts, it&#39;s not that bad, but even there the game gets a little long in the tooth. I know we live in an era when everyone seems to want games that last 120+ hours but there&#39;s a very good argument to be made that a shorter, tighter game is a stronger all-around experience. Better to be left wanting more, rather than getting the final hit in on the last boss and shouting (and this is a direct quote), &amp;quot;Oh thank god, I don&#39;t ever have to play this fucking game again!&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;It Falls Into a Classic &amp;quot;Sequel Trap&amp;quot;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s talk about shards. They&#39;re the second currency the game introduces. Hollow Knight just had geo for money. Silksong has beads for money, but also requires you to use shards if you want to employ the many tools at Hornet&#39;s disposal that complement her main attacks via needle or silk. You&#39;re capped at 800 of these shards when maxed out, and an average boss attempt or long arena will use about 100 of them assuming full use of two tools. If you run out, then you have to go farm more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This adds nothing to the game. Absolutely nothing would be lost if tools just replenished at each bench without being tied to a currency. This is a &lt;em&gt;classic&lt;/em&gt; sequel trap: adding increased complexity mostly for the sake of it, in ways that don&#39;t add to the core experience and can in fact detract from it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;If they&#39;re struggling with a boss, running out of shards is a way to nudge the player towards exploring elsewhere until they can come back with more power&amp;quot; … nah. That&#39;s maybe what it&#39;s supposed to be for but that&#39;s not how it actually works. For one thing, Silksong is not Elden Ring. There&#39;s a limit to the amount of upgrading you can actually do, and a lot of those upgrade pieces are locked behind bosses. You might be able to snag one more mask, and maybe even improve your needle, but more likely you&#39;ll just wander or, worse, farm shards until they&#39;re full again and then go back to the same boss.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Silksong is a much more mechanics-based game than Dark Souls or even Bloodborne (which also suffered from farming issues). Certainly, yes, you can and should upgrade your gear, but more often than not you&#39;ll run into a boss when you&#39;re about at the level expected to take it on. In a game where mechanics are ultimately the main factor, it makes no sense to force the player to farm. It does not add value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The result? Players hesitate to even use their tools because they don&#39;t want to &amp;quot;waste&amp;quot; shards. For more than half the boss battles, I never used a red tool at all, because I didn&#39;t want to burn the shards, even though they were maxed out. I&#39;m not alone in this - it&#39;s such a common gamer behavior that there are memes aplenty about it. &amp;quot;Lol I had fifty rockets and I beat the final boss without using any because I was afraid of wasting them&amp;quot; is a super common sentiment among video game players.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;re going to put so many fun tools into the game, you should make people want to use them! Tying them to a currency system is going to absolutely ensure that doesn&#39;t happen, at least not as much as it could. Making them a scarce resource &lt;em&gt;decreases&lt;/em&gt; the desire to use them, rather than increasing it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;It Leans Into Tedium&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two types of hard. There&#39;s &lt;em&gt;fun&lt;/em&gt; hard (or at least, &lt;em&gt;compelling&lt;/em&gt; hard), and there&#39;s &lt;em&gt;tedious&lt;/em&gt; hard. The line between these two is incredibly blurry and shifts heavily depending on the person, but I believe that Silksong fairly regularly falls pretty far on the tedious side. For every Cogwork Dancers, one of the most perfect boss battles in video game history, there is a Bilewater runback. You can justify that runback however you like. &amp;quot;Oh, Silksong is a game about suffering,&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;Oh, there&#39;s a hidden bench that only makes the runback awful instead of utterly miserable,&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;Oh, actually, I like platforming.&amp;quot; Go for it. Have a blast. That runback is tedious as shit, and the majority of players agree with me. It&#39;s not &lt;em&gt;fun&lt;/em&gt; hard. It&#39;s not even actually that hard! It&#39;s just boring, obnoxious, and frustrating. The Last Judge is fun hard. The First Sinner is fun hard (so fun!). Even Lost Lace, and again, we&#39;ll get to her, is mostly fun hard. The Bilewater runback? Tedious, man. Just deeply tedious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some other things that are tedious about Silksong:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The endless arenas. Every two feet, you&#39;re locked into another room with waves of enemies. A bunch of bosses even have waves of enemies before the boss shows up! I didn&#39;t mind the arenas in Hollow Knight because they were all pretty short (also there were about 1/12 as many, and none before bosses). Silksong will regularly throw six waves or more at you. It&#39;s not necessarily hard, depending on your skill level, but it wears out its welcome. Tedious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Surprise bench traps / broken benches. One of these is fun, especially if they&#39;re positioned in a way that makes getting back to them not too much of an ordeal, or if the tell is super obvious. Several of them, all with no tell whatsoever? Tedious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So much platforming. Listen, I get it - a lot of people thought Hollow Knight had too little platforming. A lot of people think Celeste is a fun game. Personally I&#39;d rather whale myself in the junk repeatedly, but you do you. That said, there are multiple sections of Silksong where no matter how good you are at platforming, they just drag on. Tedious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Long runbacks. Come on, man. We&#39;ve figured this out! I&#39;ve heard all kinds of justifications for this, from the old chestnut about Silksong being about suffering, to &amp;quot;it helps me clear my head between boss fights.&amp;quot; Cool. Don&#39;t care. Forcing the player to run through the same area over and over again to get back to the boss is unnecessary and doesn&#39;t contribute much of anything to the experience. When, multiple times, those areas are filled with platforming, it&#39;s just double the not-fun. Tedious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bosses with adds. I have never encountered a boss in any video game, in 40+ years of playing them, where adds made the fight more fun. Dual phase bosses? Great! Bosses where a second boss shows up midway through? Great! Bosses where they throw a bunch of standard mobs into the arena with you just to up the difficulty? Tedious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The flea circus. Man, fuck them fleas! I did all that for them and my reward is having to slog through this for a pale oil? I hope you all drown in the bath carriage! Okay, I&#39;m partially kidding here - it&#39;s a fun little addition, but locking that upgrade behind certain scores? Tedious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Filling the screen with bullshit. Okay, let&#39;s talk about Lost Lace. It took me thirty minutes to get to the point where I could reliably get her to phase three. It took me three hours to beat her. The reason wasn&#39;t because there was some amazing mechanical shift in her third phase. It was because I &lt;strong&gt;fucking couldn&#39;t see her&lt;/strong&gt;! You&#39;re fighting a black boss, who shoots black attacks, on a dark grey background, atop a black swamp. To be fair, there &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; outlines, so it&#39;s reasonably trackable. Then phase three starts, and all of a sudden, there&#39;s shit all over the place! It&#39;s so hard to see where Lace is, what she&#39;s doing, and where attacks might be coming from. The audio cues don&#39;t really help, as they don&#39;t preface specific attacks. You&#39;re left with rain, bits of silk, and random splatters all over your screen, and you basically just have to hope that you can manage to figure out what&#39;s going on long enough to get the hits in you need to make the shitshow stop. This is the worst example but not by any means the only one in the game. Te-di-ous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#39;s a lot of tedium for one game. It&#39;s made up for by a whole lot of other excellent things, but it does drag the game down a bit. You want to avoid players using terms like &amp;quot;slog,&amp;quot; &amp;quot;grind,&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;farm&amp;quot; whenever possible. Silksong mostly does. But sometimes it doesn&#39;t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Wrapup&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I may be in the minority here. Silksong is justifiably getting a lot of Game of the Year buzz, and I&#39;ve seen more than one person say they think it&#39;s the greatest game they&#39;ve ever played. I suspect that latter sentiment will dissipate somewhat as we get further out from the game&#39;s release and people have time to cool down a bit, but I&#39;m sure there will always be folks who think it&#39;s the best thing ever made. I&#39;m not one of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s take an example so old, half the people playing Silksong right now probably weren&#39;t born when the titles came out: Fallout and Fallout 2. I would say the majority sentiment is that Fallout 2 is the better game, a statement with which I &lt;em&gt;vehemently&lt;/em&gt; disagree. Fallout 2 provided a few quality of life improvements that were extremely welcome, but beyond that it is sprawling, messy, overly self-referential, and campier than the first game in a way I think detracts from the experience. It&#39;s also too long.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fallout provides a tighter, more focused experience. It is, in my opinion, the better game by a pretty wide margin. Fallout does not give you time to get bored of it. Fallout 2 very much does, and you can see things the developers put into the game specifically to combat that (the car being the most notable). It&#39;s still a spectacular game, and one of the best RPGs of all time, but in the grand tradition of sequels, it&#39;s overstuffed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Silksong feels like the Fallout 2 to Hollow Knight&#39;s Fallout. The former are both &lt;em&gt;excellent&lt;/em&gt; games. The latter are all-timers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I again want to point out that I replayed Hollow Knight &lt;em&gt;immediately&lt;/em&gt; after finishing Silksong. This isn&#39;t rose-tinted glasses. This is a direct comparison between the two games. I&#39;m very aware of Hollow Knight&#39;s faults - the knight&#39;s movement is slow and cumbersome to start the game, half the charms are basically worthless, the true ending is hidden behind a single double-jump in Kingdom&#39;s Edge that is very easy to miss, the lore is really obscure without relying on YouTube videos, and so forth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hollow Knight is not a perfect game, because perfect games don&#39;t exist, but it is in my opinion the best Metroidvania ever made and one of the greatest games of all time. Silksong is a worthy sequel. I just wish Team Cherry hadn&#39;t doubled down quite so much on the slog.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Reflections on a Year in France | Post | CWB Writing</title>
    <link href="https://cwbwriting.com/posts/2025-09-a-year-in-france/"/>
    <updated>2025-09-06T10:05:54Z</updated>
    <id>https://cwbwriting.com/posts/2025-09-a-year-in-france/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;On July 15th, 2024, my wife Charlotte and I boarded a plane to Paris with three carry-on bags and a carry-on very old cat. We&#39;d also checked four huge bags. It was a record amount of luggage for us. The reason? We were leaving the United States and, for the foreseeable future, not coming back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&#39;d sold our house, sold most of our stuff, and shipped less than a studio apartment&#39;s worth of things across the ocean. We had an apartment lined up, but would have to wait a month to move in. While we had places to stay—hotels and crashing with family—we were technically transients. On August 18th, we finally moved in and began actually getting settled. We live in Saint-Cloud, which is about a twelve-minute drive outside of Paris.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s been about a year since then. In some ways, it feels like it&#39;s been ten, in others it feels like it&#39;s been maybe two months. We spent a lot of time caring for the cat, who was quite sick, before he &lt;a href=&quot;https://cwbwriting.com/posts/2025-03-on-loss-again/&quot;&gt;finally passed in March&lt;/a&gt;. That was stressful. Charlotte started a new job at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.asparis.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;a new school&lt;/a&gt;, having to make all new lesson plans. That was stressful. I had to search for and find a job, then dive into getting to know a &lt;a href=&quot;https://embeddable.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;new product, team, and technology&lt;/a&gt;. That was stressful. There was an insane amount of bureaucracy and clerical shit to deal with. That was … you get it. Stress does weird things to time perception.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But along with all that stress there was a lot of great stuff, including adaptation to life in France. I&#39;ve done this once before: we lived here for six months from late 2015 to early 2016. But I made fewer efforts during that time to incorporate, because I knew I&#39;d be coming back. I&#39;m not sure this time. We&#39;re here till at least 2029. We might be here forever. Better learn how to be a part of the ebb and flow of the place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s nice. Life feels less precarious here. While our combined income took a hit with the move (European tech salaries are lower than US tech salaries), it doesn&#39;t matter. The cost of living is slightly lower. Our taxes pay for nationalized healthcare and other services. We don&#39;t have to, need to, or want to own a car. There are additional things I could mention. If there&#39;s been any decrease in our quality of life, I sure haven&#39;t noticed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s not all baguettes and wine (although I&#39;ve had a lot of baguettes and wine!). There are frustrations aplenty. This is true of life anywhere, and honestly day-to-day life in France is not particularly different from what it was in the US. I get up, I work out, I take a shower, I eat breakfast, and I go to work … by which I mean go to my home office, as I&#39;ve been fully remote since 2010. It&#39;s just that if I look out our living room window from the right angle, I can see the Eiffel Tower.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are small differences, though. The produce is, on average, much better here. Ice cubes are rare - you might get one or two if you order a Coke or Perrier at a café. Decent Mexican food is almost impossible to find, but high-quality Vietnamese is everywhere. The cars are smaller and there are virtually no pickup trucks, although the SUV plague is encroaching, especially in rich areas. The bread, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Viennoiserie&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;viennoiseries&lt;/a&gt; (what Americans call “pastries”) and pastries (what Americans call “dessert”) are, on average, mind-blowing. The meat is better, more ethically treated, and much less likely to give you food poisoning. The seafood is unbelievable. You can get a COVID vaccine without having to fight RFK Jr. in a steel cage match. No one has guns. No one worries about anyone else having guns. No one &lt;strong&gt;wants&lt;/strong&gt; to have guns. Most people get six weeks of vacation, and most people actually take them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can&#39;t buy anything even vaguely medical in a grocery store, not even antacid. Got heartburn on a Sunday night? You&#39;re hoofing it to whatever 24-hour pharmacy might be within 100 miles of you, or you&#39;re eating baking soda straight out the package (which you &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; buy in the grocery store, but only in the cleaning section). If you want some Advil, you can only buy it in packs of 12 at a time, each pill individually blister-wrapped. The pharmacist will solemnly tell you to take one tablet no more than every six hours, with plenty of water, and never on an empty stomach. She will also recommend a homeopathic alternative for some reason. You will thank her, walk out the door, and immediately dry-swallow four tablets having eaten nothing for the last half day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But when you go to fill a prescription, the same pharmacist will note that you haven&#39;t received your &lt;em&gt;carte vitale&lt;/em&gt; yet so they have to charge you full price. She will apologize repeatedly and insist you keep the receipt so that when you do get your medical card, you can get reimbursed. She will be appalled that the French bureaucracy, in its eternal slowness, has failed you in this manner. The terrible full cost you pay for the meds will be … nine euro.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is absolutely no goddamn culture here whatsoever of getting out of people&#39;s way. No one cares that they are holding a hundred people up by calmly reorganizing their entire wallet after paying for their cheese purchase at the busiest market in human history. No one cares that they are taking up the entire sidewalk standing around talking, forcing you into a busy street with two suitcases and a backpack. Not the world&#39;s oldest woman who is telling her life story to a post office employee while a line thirteen deep forms behind her, not the teens kicking a soccer ball around in the middle of a crowded subway interchange, and not the 30-something guy on your morning run who is taking up the entire sidewalk while putting the “stroll” in “pushing a stroller.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But people will always say &lt;em&gt;bonjour&lt;/em&gt; when you enter a store, or sometimes just pass them on the sidewalk. All but the most obnoxious of Parisian waiters in the worst tourist areas will appreciate your speaking in French and compliment your mediocre attempts. The guy running the wine store on the corner will spend 20 minutes helping you narrow down the bottle that will please both your 78-year-old traditionalist father-in-law and your gourmand brother-in-law, and then will recommend five others you should try. You will trip in a parking lot, scrape up your hand, and be absolutely swarmed by people reacting like your arm was torn fully off and they have only minutes in which to save your life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On top of the cultural differences big and small, there have been events of all types. We&#39;re able to see Charlotte&#39;s family more easily and more regularly now, which has been nice, even if big gatherings of people all speaking in rapid-fire French are still intimidating for me. We also got to host several members of &lt;em&gt;my&lt;/em&gt; family who made the trek over from the US in April, which was awesome. We&#39;ve also made some new friends, and reconnected with some old ones, hosting several get-togethers at our place and attending several others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Around New Year&#39;s we visited &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saint-Malo&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Saint-Malo&lt;/a&gt; on the northern Brittany coast, which was lovely despite the time of year and my battling a nasty cold. This summer, we had the opportunity to take a long weekend in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ch%C3%A2teauroux&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;central France&lt;/a&gt; where we did everything from hiking to exploring &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.chambord.org/fr/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Chateau de Chambord&lt;/a&gt;. We will surely see more parts of the country that we&#39;ve not been to before. We&#39;ve been able to visit other European destinations more easily, too, taking trips to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malta&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Malta&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Latvia&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Latvia&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Estonia&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Estonia&lt;/a&gt; so far. I&#39;ve been to both &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Berlin&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Berlin&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barcelona&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Barcelona&lt;/a&gt; for work get-togethers, and will be in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alicante&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Alicante, Spain&lt;/a&gt;, for a &lt;a href=&quot;https://reactalicante.es/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;tech conference&lt;/a&gt; soon. In between all that, we regularly get into Paris proper for shows, basketball games, movies, and more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, I&#39;ve had an amazing first year and I feel genuinely blessed to have this opportunity. I can&#39;t wait to see what the next year brings. I just hope it comes with a little less stress. I&#39;d like the time to slow down, a bit, so things are more relaxed. There&#39;s a lot to enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>On Loss ... Again | Post | CWB Writing</title>
    <link href="https://cwbwriting.com/posts/2025-03-on-loss-again/"/>
    <updated>2025-03-25T19:16:57Z</updated>
    <id>https://cwbwriting.com/posts/2025-03-on-loss-again/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Content Warning: Loss of Pet&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best cat is your cat. Let&#39;s put that out there, first. The best cat is always &lt;em&gt;your&lt;/em&gt; cat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;… but Baron was the best cat. I think this is true on an objective scale. He was sweet, and kind, and loving, and followed you from room to room just to be close to you, and made little inquisitive chirping noises, and up until just the very end he wasn&#39;t demanding, or dirty, or hard to care for. In his prime he was an athlete. I once saw that dude leap four feet into the air and bat a moth to the ground. This was not a small cat! He was more Shaq than MJ, but nonetheless. Athlete.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He did leave an occasional ball of poop on the floor when it got stuck in his ass hair, but listen, nobody&#39;s perfect. I didn&#39;t say he was the perfect cat. I said he was the best cat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was not the best owner. &lt;a href=&quot;https://cwbwriting.com/posts/2023-02-on-loss/&quot;&gt;We covered this when we lost our other cat, Carbomb, two years ago&lt;/a&gt;. But Carbomb&#39;s passing helped me to really appreciate Baron, and to understand how much I loved the big guy. As Charlotte put it: That&#39;s a pretty solid legacy for her. It is, and I&#39;m deeply thankful for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Baron was born on the mean streets of Brooklyn - he was found in an abandoned lot in a not-so-great part of town by a lady who lived in a two bedroom apartment with (I am not exaggerating here), no fewer than thirty-five other cats. Also two Rottweilers. She wasn&#39;t the ASPCA but she was affiliated with them in the loose sense that they trusted her to actually get the cats she was &lt;strike&gt;hoarding&lt;/strike&gt; adopting out vaccinated, and would certify them for her. We visited her to meet another cat who we saw online. He wouldn&#39;t come out from under the bed. We were about to leave and she was like &amp;quot;hey, I have this kitten … I haven&#39;t filled out all the paperwork yet and would just as soon not. Do you want to meet him?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He came home with us that night. We, being idiots, were like, &amp;quot;Cool, here you go. Litterbox is in the bathroom, food and water&#39;s in the kitchen, the other cat&#39;s around here somewhere. See you tomorrow.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next morning, we found him huddled behind the toilet, Carbomb sitting about four feet from him and staring at him with the kind of intensity that ex-cops on a revenge spree reserve for the guy who killed their spouse. He spent the next several days living in our bedroom closet. At night, he would come out and attack my feet as they moved under the covers. I&#39;m a restless sleeper, so this happened a lot. Ultimately he and Carbomb came to a truce, and he moved out into the rest of our Brooklyn apartment. From there he came with us to Indianapolis, and then to Providence. He was with us on our six-month stint in Paris in 2016, and with us again when we moved here full-time in July 2024.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He grew from a timid little baby to an also-timid cat-Shaq. Eventually he became a still-timid old man. But he wasn&#39;t timid with the people he knew and loved. With us, he was in his comfort zone. We never got the cold shoulder after a trip. It was always &amp;quot;oh, thank god, you&#39;re back.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Baron passed away this evening. I don&#39;t believe in an afterlife but I would &lt;em&gt;like&lt;/em&gt; to, and one of the reasons I would like to is that it&#39;d be nice to see both him and Carbomb again. I would like to laugh again as he wanders by her, not even paying attention, and she reaches out and whacks him in the face just to remind him who runs the show … and then curls up next to him on the couch for four hours later that evening. I would like to see him again in his prime, utterly destroying an alpine scratcher in a handful of weeks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post will not be as long as the one I wrote two years ago, not because I loved Baron any less or am any less saddened and distressed by his loss. I have all the same feelings of terror that we made the call too early. The house feels just as weird and quiet and empty as it did when Carbomb passed. I have the same sweeping waves of sadness. I regret every single time I lost my cool and yelled, every single time in the final months when I felt like him peeing on something was a personal attack even when I knew it wasn&#39;t. But I know that I loved him, and I know he knew that I loved him, and I know that Charlotte and I fought for him and for his comfort. Pills, liquids, injections, prescription foods, comfy mats in the incredibly inconvenient places he most liked to sleep, pee pads for his accidents, lap time when he asked for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I know that he loved me. I always knew that about Carbomb. She wore her heart on her sleeve for me. I guess I always knew it about Baron, too, but he was so much Charlotte&#39;s cat. Ever since I accidentally poisoned him when he was a kitten by dropping an ibuprofen on the bathroom floor while in a rush one morning and going &amp;quot;eh, I&#39;ll get that later,&amp;quot; and she spent the next several days nursing him back to health after the dumbass ate it, he was &lt;em&gt;her&lt;/em&gt; cat. I don&#39;t know that I&#39;ve ever seen a cat love anyone more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But he loved me, too. Sometimes he would spend a while in her lap and then be like &amp;quot;a&#39;ight but that guy needs me too,&amp;quot; and make the switch. I&#39;ve worked from home since 2010 and sometimes he and I would have what felt like actual conversations when I got up to make a cup of coffee, or get my lunch, or use the bathroom. I had a habit of randomly telling him &amp;quot;your new name will be&amp;quot; and then coming up with the dumbest shit. &amp;quot;Lord High Admiral Fondledonk&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;Chairman Meo&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;Fatbasket&amp;quot;. He took that in stride. I genuinely don&#39;t know who I&#39;m going to talk to during the day, now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&#39;t believe in an afterlife, but I would like to. I like to think he&#39;d be there, waiting patiently, and when either of us finally arrived, we&#39;d get that same response we always did. &amp;quot;Oh, thank god, you&#39;re back.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I miss you, big guy. I love you. You were the best.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://cwbwriting.com/_img/baron_memorial.jpg&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; style=&quot;width: 100%&quot; /&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>CWB Writing Newsletter - May 2023 | Post | CWB Writing</title>
    <link href="https://cwbwriting.com/posts/2023-05-cwb-writing-newsletter-march-2023/"/>
    <updated>2023-06-24T20:41:38Z</updated>
    <id>https://cwbwriting.com/posts/2023-05-cwb-writing-newsletter-march-2023/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Going to hammer out a quick newsletter for y&#39;all because somehow it&#39;s May 30th, when it feels like yesterday was late April!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Working With Diana&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As mentioned in the last newsletter, in February I signed with Diana Fox of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.publishersmarketplace.com/members/fox/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Fox Literary&lt;/a&gt; to represent &lt;em&gt;Piety the Knife&lt;/em&gt;, its sequel, and my future work to publishers. Since then we&#39;ve gone over not just Piety the Knife, but also its sequel, and talked about plans. One plan we&#39;ve talked about: possibly converting the sequel to the third book in the trilogy, and converting the plan for the third book into the second, which is kind of crazy but might be the right move! She&#39;s very excited about the plot outline for what is currently the third book, much of which is a flashback, and thinks it might hit the reader harder if we kind of smash-cut right from Piety to that. I need to ponder it a bit more and decide if it makes sense with my overall plan for the story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, I have lots of great feedback on the sequel I &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; write, including a whole bunch of thoughts on what to cut, what to expand, and what to tweak. I&#39;m holding off on a second draft right now for two reasons. First, the whole &amp;quot;this might actually end up being the third book in the trilogy&amp;quot; thing. Second, we want to get Piety all finished up before focusing on anything else. So, let&#39;s talk about that!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Piety the Knife - Final Tweaks&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Diana provided me a lot of good feedback on Piety as well. She&#39;s really happy with the latest draft, and only wants a few relatively minor changes before it&#39;s time to shop it to publishers. She&#39;s still in the process of getting her line edits together, but in the interim, we had a Zoom call to talk about overall thoughts, which has allowed me to get started with some edits in advance of getting her final redline document. I&#39;m working on those edits now, and we&#39;re hoping to have the book stable and ready to go out on submission by mid-to-late-June. Pretty cool!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If it &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; get picked up by a publisher, there will no doubt be further revisions. Any book you&#39;ve ever read, at least any traditionally-published book, is the product of numerous people&#39;s hard work. The author gets the majority of the credit, and of course it &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; their story, but in nearly all cases there is an editor or set of editors who contribute substantially to the final manuscript. I&#39;m looking forward to experiencing that part of the process, so … fingers crossed we get there!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Possessed - Indie Release?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also talked with Diana about the possibility of indie-publishing Possessed. She doesn&#39;t have an issue with the idea, as contemporary fantasy is a very popular indie genre but a very hard sell to traditional publishers. SO … this means I might be able to get it out to you folks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That does come with some complications: I&#39;m not willing to put the book out without running it through professional editing services. I&#39;m looking at over a thousand bucks for that, plus likely a similar number to pay a cover artist (I don&#39;t really want to do the cover myself like I did with Elixir, and I &lt;a href=&quot;https://cwbwriting.com/posts/2022-12-on-ai-art/&quot;&gt;already talked about why I don&#39;t support AI art over on my blog&lt;/a&gt;). That&#39;s some serious scratch, especially for a book that may or may not sell. I don&#39;t necessarily care about recouping the cost, but I need to be able to actually pay it, which means I need to do some saving!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Book Recommendation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking of indie releases, my friend Zach Argyle wrapped up an incredibly successful kickstarter for gorgeous new editions of his fantasy series, Threadlight. If you just want to read the books, though (and I recommend you do), you can get them on Amazon individually or as an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Threadlight-Trilogy-Epic-Fantasy-Boxset-ebook/dp/B0BH3SW5XF&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;ebook box set&lt;/a&gt; for a ridiculously low $4.99. They&#39;re cool books! Definitely worth a look if you&#39;re into swords and sorcery with a lot of fun world building and solid characters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#39;s it for now. See you in July. Hopefully sometime before the last two days of the month!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;-Chris&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;You can get these updates before they hit the blog by subscribing to the newsletter!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>How I Got My Agent</title>
    <link href="https://cwbwriting.com/posts/2023-04-how_i_got_my_agent/"/>
    <updated>2023-06-24T20:41:23Z</updated>
    <id>https://cwbwriting.com/posts/2023-04-how_i_got_my_agent/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;How did you get your agent?&amp;quot; is a question that writers with agents hear a lot. There are really three answers to it: short, shortish, and long as hell. I&#39;m here to provide you all three today!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, the short answer? Hard work and luck.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The shortish answer? I wrote several books, queried dozens of agents for each of them, and finally found someone who clicked with my work at such a time that a) she was looking for new clients, b) she wanted to represent a dark fantasy novel, and c) she thinks the market will be interested in a dark fantasy novel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&#39;t think either of those answers are really what people are looking for, though, because it&#39;s human nature to believe there&#39;s some secret sauce — some magical thing they can do that will tilt the odds in their favor. Look, for example, at all the people asking talented artists &amp;quot;how did you learn to draw so well?&amp;quot; as if the answer is anything other than &amp;quot;I drew, and drew, and drew, all the time, every day, for years of my life, while also studying anatomy, proportion, perspective, and all of the other things one needs to study in order to get good.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no shortcut. But still, the question is interesting, and the answers often are as well. Every journey is different, even if those journeys often have similar structures. So … how did I get my agent? Well, let me tell you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Between 2009 and 2013, I self-published four novels. The first three, &lt;a href=&quot;https://cwbwriting.com/books/2amtrilogy/&quot;&gt;a trilogy of action-packed, sexy vampire novels&lt;/a&gt;, had found quite a significant audience. The fourth, a young-adult sci-fi novel set in a far-future broken world, had not resonated with that audience and not sold particularly well. Alas! But I don&#39;t really care; it&#39;s a good book and I like it, and I&#39;ve never seen this gig as a primary source of income so sales numbers aren&#39;t really my main focus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I digress. I decided after &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cwbwriting.com/books/thebrokengodmachine/&quot;&gt;The Broken God Machine&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; that I wanted to get back to pursuing traditional publishing. It&#39;s been a dream of mine since I was eleven years old to see one of my books on the shelf with a publisher&#39;s imprint on it. It feels &amp;quot;real&amp;quot; to me in a way that the self-publishing just doesn&#39;t, even though Blood Hunt in particular has sold more copies than an absolute &lt;em&gt;ton&lt;/em&gt; of traditionally published books.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, when I wrote my next book, &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cwbwriting.com/books/elixir/&quot;&gt;Elixir&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, I didn&#39;t immediately self-publish it. Instead, I sent it to &lt;a href=&quot;https://petergelfan.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Peter Gelfan&lt;/a&gt;, a talented editor who freelances for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.editorialdepartment.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Editorial Department&lt;/a&gt;. Over the course of two edits on the manuscript, he gave me an immense amount of incredibly valuable insight into writing that I still use to this day. &lt;em&gt;Elixir&lt;/em&gt; may not be better than my previous works in terms of how much it connects with readers, but from a technical standpoint it is immensely superior, and I think that&#39;s carried on to all of my works since. Side note: I know not every writer is lucky enough to have the disposable income to pay for a professional editing pass, let alone multiple ones, but if you can … do it. You will not regret it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given the multiple rounds of editing, it&#39;s perhaps no surprise that &lt;em&gt;Elixir&lt;/em&gt; was also the first book I enjoyed any particular success with when querying agents. &lt;em&gt;The Broken God Machine&lt;/em&gt;, which I did query to about thirty agents, got a single request for the full manuscript but no offers of representation. Elixir went out to fifty-five agents, which yielded five &amp;quot;full requests.&amp;quot; An astounding three of those turned into offers of representation. I eventually signed with Kirsten Carleton, then of Waxman-Leavell (now just &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.waxmanliteraryagency.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Waxman Literary&lt;/a&gt;) but who shortly after moved to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.prospectagency.com/submit.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Prospect Agency&lt;/a&gt;. We put the finishing touches on &lt;em&gt;Elixir&lt;/em&gt; and sent it out to acquisitions editors at several publishers, big and small, some that leaned more toward Sci-Fi, and some that leaned more toward thrillers (the book straddles the line).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What followed was a series of what I call &amp;quot;glowing rejections&amp;quot; - almost invariably, we&#39;d get a paragraph of praise for the book, followed by, &amp;quot;but I&#39;m not sure how to sell it&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;but we&#39;re not sure it&#39;s right for our audience,&amp;quot; followed by a pass. This went on and on. Ultimately, the book didn&#39;t sell. I think it may&#39;ve been too Sci-Fi for the thriller folks and too thriller for the Sci-Fi folks, or it may just have been bad timing, or who knows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I wrote another book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pulse&lt;/em&gt; is a Sci-Fi horror novel that initially seems to be a zombie book, but eventually becomes something else. Kirsten and I worked it through several drafts, until we felt it was ready to go, and then once again sent it off to acquisitions editors. Once again, the glowing rejections rolled in. Seriously, I mean … look at this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you so much for sharing PULSE with me. I just love how the manuscript opens with that great, foreboding prologue. … Plus, the early puzzle pieces (the grid that only some folks can see, the singing, the time jump for Raine) provide a lot of room for readers to bring their own imaginations to bear. And what works particularly well is that final twist: [spoilers!]. This subverts expectations in a satisfying way, just like the revelation that [more spoilers!].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&#39;t know about you but that doesn&#39;t read like a rejection to me. Nonetheless, that&#39;s what it was, and I once again ended up with a book that got a lot of praise but did not ultimately sell. Discouraging! But here&#39;s the thing: the publishing industry is a fickle, capricious beast. All you can do is roll with the punches and keep trying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I wrote another book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This one, &lt;em&gt;Divergence Point&lt;/em&gt;, is a pretty classic space opera. It&#39;s a little more grounded than, say, Star Wars – there&#39;s no magic (which, let&#39;s be honest, is what the Force is). I&#39;d compare it to the Mass Effect video games, although none of my alien species look exactly like humans except with squid tentacles for hair. It features a terrorist, an assassin, and a hacker who&#39;re recruited by a shadow government to hijack an alien ark and steal its warp drive. It&#39;s a really fun book and I like it a lot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sadly, before we could send that one out to publishers, Kirsten wound up leaving the publishing business for personal reasons. This put me back at square one. You&#39;d think &amp;quot;oh, well, at least having had an agent probably gives you a leg up&amp;quot; right? NOPE! The thing is that the agent/writer connection is a really personal thing. Agents see dozens if not hundreds of writers a year who are &lt;em&gt;good writers&lt;/em&gt; … that&#39;s simply not enough. They need to click with the voice, with the genre, with the plot. They need someone who&#39;s writing in a genre that they can sell, and who isn&#39;t writing in the same genre as someone else they just signed. There are dozens of factors that go into an agent&#39;s decision to offer representation, and &amp;quot;this guy already broke through that barrier once&amp;quot; turns out to be a very minor factor, if any factor at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I queried &lt;em&gt;Divergence Point&lt;/em&gt;. I contacted eighty-three agents. I got three full requests. I got no offers of representation and only a single personalized piece of feedback (the other two rejections were form letters).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I wrote another book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Possessed&lt;/em&gt; is a contemporary fantasy about a young woman who becomes accidentally possessed by a demon. It&#39;s a fun, funny, fast-paced book in the vein of Christopher Moore. It is also, as it turns out, in a genre that is considered almost completely unsellable in traditional publishing at the moment (contemporary or &amp;quot;urban&amp;quot; fantasy is a HUGE genre; it&#39;s just dominated almost entirely by indie authors who crank out five books a year about, like, werewolf hunters who might also want to bang the werewolf they&#39;re hunting).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not knowing this, I queried &lt;em&gt;Possessed&lt;/em&gt; widely as well. This one went out to forty-five agents. It did get some interest! Two full requests and a partial manuscript request. Sadly, all forty-five of those agents ultimately passed on it. Including an agent named Diana Fox, of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.publishersmarketplace.com/members/fox/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Fox Literary&lt;/a&gt;, who had also passed on &lt;em&gt;Divergence Point&lt;/em&gt;. More on that in a second.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we&#39;re keeping count here, by this point in the story I have eight books under my belt: &lt;em&gt;The Blood That Bonds&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Blood Hunt&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;The Children of the Sun&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;The Broken God Machine&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Elixir&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Pulse&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Divergence Point&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Possessed&lt;/em&gt;. But I actually have nine, because I also wrote the first draft of a young adult book called &lt;em&gt;The Werewolf at the Window&lt;/em&gt;, which I&#39;ve never even written a second draft on, much less queried. Each manuscript (that I hadn&#39;t self-published) was getting interest from agents or publishers, but none had made it over the hump.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I wrote another book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Piety the Knife&lt;/em&gt; is a dark fantasy novel heavily inspired by the Dark Souls series of video games. It features a crew of seven people trained in specific disciplines and sent out to return a deposed queen to her throne. It is grim and gory, with a magic system chock full of body horror, and I love it. Might be my favorite book I&#39;ve ever written. I wrote multiple drafts of it before sending it out to agents. One hundred and friggin&#39; eight agents, to be precise. Just a ridiculous number, but there are a LOT of agents who represent fantasy, so I had a lot of options.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The manuscript received six full requests, one partial request, and one &amp;quot;I would ask for a full because I&#39;ve really liked your previous submissions but I just signed a fantasy author&amp;quot; response. By a pretty wide margin the best response I&#39;ve ever received! Awesome, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of those agents eventually passed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of them except Diana Fox, who responded going &amp;quot;there&#39;s something here but what you&#39;ve written is a video game in book form. I need an actual book. Let&#39;s see if you have the chops to make that change.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is called a &amp;quot;revise and resubmit&amp;quot; – an agent likes what you have but thinks it needs significant changes to actually be marketable to publishers. This is a big test for an author, and it raises a big question: can you accept that this is a business and that you may have to make fairly sweeping changes in order to be successful, or are you too bound up in your work to make those changes? Many authors can&#39;t make the changes. That is &lt;em&gt;totally okay&lt;/em&gt;! There are a zillion REALLY EXCELLENT books out there that are not marketable to publishers for one reason or another (&amp;quot;way too long&amp;quot; being one of the most common). Many of them find tremendous success as indie releases. It&#39;s fine to not want to play within the rules of traditional publishing. They&#39;re extremely restrictive, usually frustrating, and often completely baffling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But god damn it, I&#39;ve wanted my name and a publisher&#39;s imprint on the spine of a book since I was eleven. Years. Old.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More than that, though, Diana was right about &lt;em&gt;Piety&lt;/em&gt;. Turns out when you&#39;ve been doing this for almost twenty years, you have some valuable knowledge to impart, and she imparted it upon me. The book as it stood was &amp;quot;travel, boss fight, rest, travel, boss fight, rest&amp;quot; … over and over again. All of it was compelling, but the structure didn&#39;t work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I rewrote it. Chopped it up, sewed it back together. Frankensteined the motherfucker. Improved the main character&#39;s arc, added additional scenes to flesh out secondary characters, merged two &amp;quot;bosses&amp;quot; into one fight. Cleared up some questions and inconsistencies. Strengthened a bunch of scenes. The book went from 96,000 words to 105,000 words, but it&#39;s not just that I added nine thousand words. I actually cut at least five thousand. It never quite reached what happened with &lt;em&gt;The Children of the Sun&lt;/em&gt;, where between the penultimate and final draft I literally highlighted an entire chapter and hit &amp;quot;delete&amp;quot; … but it came close. I rebuilt the book, and the result is better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Better enough to land me an offer of representation from Diana. She knows now that I can do the work. She knows I &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; do the work. That, in combination with how much she likes the book itself and, just as crucially, her belief that she can sell it, was enough to get me that offer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, that&#39;s how I got my agent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From here, we make a final few tweaks to the manuscript and then we go back to the next crapshoot: trying to get a publisher to buy the book. I&#39;m cautiously optimistic. &lt;em&gt;Piety&lt;/em&gt; is good, y&#39;all. It&#39;s a really good book. I&#39;m very proud of it. But it&#39;s fully possible it won&#39;t sell. If so, it goes in the trunk, along with the sequel, the first draft of which I&#39;ve already written (for those keeping count, that puts me up to eleven). Maybe that&#39;ll be how it goes. If so, well, at least I have Diana&#39;s support for what will come next. And you know what that is; it&#39;s been a bit of a running theme throughout this post, and honestly, it&#39;s coming regardless. If &lt;em&gt;Piety&lt;/em&gt; and its sequel sell or if they do not, the result is the same. What am I going to do?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Write another book.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>CWB Writing Newsletter - March 2023 | Post | CWB Writing</title>
    <link href="https://cwbwriting.com/posts/2023-03-cwb-writing-newsletter-march-2023/"/>
    <updated>2023-06-24T20:41:23Z</updated>
    <id>https://cwbwriting.com/posts/2023-03-cwb-writing-newsletter-march-2023/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have a &lt;em&gt;ton&lt;/em&gt; of great updates in this newsletter, so let&#39;s dive right in!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I Have an Agent Again!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh, man, I can&#39;t tell you how thrilled I am to say that in February I signed with Diana Fox of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.publishersmarketplace.com/members/fox/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Fox Literary&lt;/a&gt; to represent &lt;em&gt;Piety the Knife&lt;/em&gt;, its sequel, and my future work to publishers. Diana is a massive book enthusiast, a talented editor, and an established agent with over fifteen years of experience in the industry who knows how to get books sold. She&#39;s already helped me significantly improve &lt;em&gt;Piety the Knife&lt;/em&gt; and I expect our final round of tweaks before we send it out to acquisition editors is going to really polish it to a mirror shine. I&#39;ll write more about the whole acquisition process in May&#39;s newsletter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s been five years since I lost my previous agent, the terrific Kirsten Carleton, with whom I shopped Elixir and Pulse to publishers. That was a heavier blow then I realized at the time (and it felt pretty heavy even back in early 2017 when it happened). While we were unsuccessful in selling either of those two books, I nonetheless thought Kirsten was a great agent who really helped me write some terrific stuff. I was sorry to lose her for her editing chops, her tireless enthusiasm, and of course her role as an agent that allowed me to get my work in front of publishers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;d thought, back then, that having already landed one agent would make it easier to land another. Nope! Turns out, it doesn&#39;t really matter if you&#39;ve previously had representation or not. You still have to have the right book, at the right time, for the right person, in order to find that connection that&#39;ll allow you to build a long-term relationship. Over the last five years, I&#39;ve queried literally hundreds of agents with three different books (&lt;em&gt;Piety the Knife&lt;/em&gt; alone went out to sixty-nine different agents at more than fifty agencies). Over the course of all that querying, I did receive some interest here and there, but ultimately no offers of representation until now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SO ... whew! That&#39;s a huge load off my mind. I&#39;m so excited to move back into the next phase of my publishing journey, and I hope I&#39;ll very soon have even more great news on that front. Fingers crossed!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;All books FREE on Smashwords!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, the title really says it all. From today (March 5th) to March 11th, all of my indie-published books, including the 2 AM Trilogy, The 2 AM short story Erinyes, The Broken God Machine, and Elixir, will be &lt;strong&gt;completely free&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.smashwords.com/profile/view/cwbuecheler&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;over on Smashwords&lt;/a&gt;. If you have any kind of eReader, tablet, or phone, Smashwords has a format that will work. Kindle, Boox, Nook, Kobo … etc, etc, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not really a whole lot more to say here. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.smashwords.com/profile/view/cwbuecheler&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Go snag some free books!&lt;/a&gt; And after you read one you haven&#39;t read before, reply to this newsletter and let me know what you thought of it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Piety the Knife&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As mentioned, Diana and I will be working on a final revision of &lt;em&gt;Piety&lt;/em&gt;. This shouldn&#39;t take too long - from what she&#39;s told me so far, her notes aren&#39;t going to require incredible changes. This is truly a polishing step, not really a fourth draft. She expects to have her notes together by mid-March, at which point I&#39;ll dive into the work. I&#39;m &lt;em&gt;extremely&lt;/em&gt; enthusiastic to work on this project, so I don&#39;t anticipate it taking me very long to get it done!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really like &lt;em&gt;Piety the Knife&lt;/em&gt;. I think it may be the best book I&#39;ve ever written, and I think it has an excellent chance of actually getting picked up by a publisher. All that said, as I learned with Elixir and Pulse, there are absolutely no guarantees! The publishing industry is in a constant state of flux, and it&#39;s important to remember that at its core, it&#39;s a business, and all businesses are about one thing: making money. If they don&#39;t think they can sell your book, they&#39;re not going to buy it. So, even once you have an agent, it&#39;s still a crapshoot. The agent just gets you in the door at the casino!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Piety the Knife Sequel&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my &lt;a href=&quot;https://cwbwriting.com/posts/2023-01-cwb-writing-newsletter-january-2023/&quot;&gt;last newsletter&lt;/a&gt;, I talked about how I was embarking on the sequel to &lt;em&gt;Piety&lt;/em&gt; even though I didn&#39;t yet have an agent, and how that might be a bad idea. WELP! Turns out it wasn&#39;t. I had an absolute blast writing this first draft, cranking out words at an incredible rate. The draft came in at about 129k words, which is exactly what I expected. I think it&#39;s an awesome expansion on the world established in the first book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve already collected feedback from my wife on the new book, and will soon be getting feedback from Diana and from my advance readers. She was thrilled that I&#39;d already started in on the sequel, as it&#39;ll allow us to seed some neat stuff from book two into the first one, and it&#39;s also appealing to publishers to have works in a series already in progress. So, good news all around there! More on this one in the May newsletter, also.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And finally, I have a …&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Book Recommendation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a ton of writers I enjoy and whose skills I envy, but there aren&#39;t that many who are so good that they often make me pause mid-reading to go &amp;quot;Damn, I will never be this good.&amp;quot; Geoge Saunders is one of those writers. His short speculative fiction is often so perfectly-written, all the way from concept to the construction of each sentence, that it&#39;s jaw-dropping. In his &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.indiebound.org/book/9780525509592&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;latest collection of short stories, Liberation Day&lt;/a&gt;, he repeatedly explores themes of human beings as unknowing or disposable cogs in a machine, and the inner thoughts of others. It&#39;s a masterful collection of stories that all feature speculative elements but also feel very close to home. I recommend it wholeheartedly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Catch you in May!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;-Chris&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;You can get these updates before they hit the blog by subscribing to the newsletter!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>On Loss | Post | CWB Writing</title>
    <link href="https://cwbwriting.com/posts/2023-02-on-loss/"/>
    <updated>2023-02-11T16:26:05Z</updated>
    <id>https://cwbwriting.com/posts/2023-02-on-loss/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Content Warning: Loss of Pet&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a long post and there is nothing new or revelatory in it – any pet owner who&#39;s experienced this loss will have a similar story, and I&#39;m unsure that it&#39;s of particular interest to anyone but myself. That said, writing is part of how I work through things, and I need to work through this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Monday morning, February 6th 2023, my wife and I got up and went about our normal routines. She was working from home due to a pipe break at her school. I was working at home because I have worked from home full-time since 2011. We went about our morning routine. I worked out, ran, and took a shower. She fed the cats—Carbomb, a female tortie almost 17 years old, and Baron Salvatore H. Lynx II, a male Maine coon almost 15 years old—made coffee and breakfast for herself, and got set up to work from her office upstairs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometime shortly after my shower, Carbomb made a strange noise and then barfed up her breakfast. This was, in itself, not a terribly unusual event. She&#39;s been a pukey cat her entire life, prone to scarfing and barfing (yes, we&#39;d checked with multiple vets about it, and their response was a uniform &amp;quot;there&#39;s nothing wrong with her, some cats just puke a lot&amp;quot;). So, we cleaned things up and went about our day, until about an hour later we noticed she was behaving oddly. She was unsteady on her feet, didn&#39;t seem to realize where she was, and kept getting stuck in corners and then giving a single upset shout about it. Because she was an old cat, and because it was such a wide swing in behavior even from the previous morning, we scheduled a vet appointment that day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A little background: We adopted Carbomb in the spring of 2007, when she was about a year old. We went to the ASPCA on the upper east side of Manhattan with the intention of finding a cat, walked into the cat room, and she leapt down from a perch and walked on top of several other, less enthusiastic cats to greet us. We did at least &amp;quot;interview&amp;quot; a few other cats but the deal was pretty much sealed from the start. She was the one. We called her Carbomb because her fur was the color of Guinness, Bailey&#39;s, and Jameson. She&#39;d been a constant part of our life for nearly sixteen years, moving with us from Manhattan, to Brooklyn, to Indianapolis, to Providence, and even making a six-month trip with us to Paris (her brother was also there for all of the stops except Manhattan).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Carbomb had been acting &amp;quot;old&amp;quot; for several months at this point. She had trouble getting up on the couch, and her counter-hopping days were years past. She had become picky about where she spent her time, living mostly in her heated bed or on the couch in my office (the warmest room in the house). She would still chase treats if we bounced them along our hardwood floor, but she mostly found them by sound and movement. If they came to a complete stop, she would lose them. She had no major health issues that we knew about, although a few months ago we did find her holed up and looking unwell at the bottom of our front stairs, the coldest part of our house (a trip to the animal ER showed nothing wrong with her bloodwork, and only that she was a bit dehydrated). So, nothing crazy for a cat that was pushing seventeen. We figured her eyes were just going a bit, the way her legs had been for years now. She was still a vibrant, active, responsive cat. Now, very suddenly, she wasn&#39;t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The vet inspected her and diagnosed her with, essentially, &amp;quot;seizure hangover&amp;quot; - she thought Carbomb had experienced a significant seizure that morning (thus the weird noise before the puking) and was still recovering. Typically, she said, the recovery would take a day or so, though there was no guarantee how complete it would be, or that it would happen at all. When Charlotte asked her what the likely cause was, she said unfortunately the most likely cause was brain tumors (not necessarily cancerous), but it wouldn&#39;t be possible to know without doing an MRI. Charlotte said she&#39;d talk everything over with me, and brought Carbomb home. The vet had given her some valium to relax her, and once we got her someplace comfortable, she mostly slept for the rest of the night. She was uninterested in food or water, and we didn&#39;t push her to eat or drink.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday, it became apparent that our cat was not recovering. For one thing, she was completely blind. For another, she was having difficulty walking, and even when standing still would often sway. When asleep, which was often, she seemed fine. When she decided she wanted to move, she would walk slowly in a near-straight line, listing slightly to the right, until she reached an obstacle (usually by running face-first into it). At that point, she would clumsily attempt to scale the obstacle, whether it was a shoe, a stool, or a wall. Several times she walked right through her own water bowl, not noticing her wet paws. She frequently became trapped in corners and would then yell, but it was apparent she didn&#39;t even really know what she was yelling about. She remained unresponsive to our voices, though we could tell by head and ear twitches she could at least hear. She did seem to take comfort in being on us. Whenever one of us sat with her on our chest, she would promptly fall asleep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tuesday night, Charlotte &amp;quot;fed&amp;quot; her by jamming a few fingers of wet food down her gullet. She swallowed them with difficulty but had no real interest in the food itself. We resorted to using a medication syringe to jet water into her mouth, which was the only way to get her to drink. She did not groom. She did not use the litter box. She did not really react to stimulus including being picked up or otherwise interacted with, other than the aforementioned falling asleep when she was on us. We tried anti-inflammatories in case her brain had swelled, and we tried phenobarbital, a common seizure suppressant, even though it mostly only works for epilepsy and Carbomb did not have epilepsy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Wednesday, there was no improvement. In the afternoon I was able to get her to take a few licks from a plate of water by essentially holding it directly up to her face. I also crushed up several of her favorite treats and got her to take a few half-hearted bites of them. In all, she was unable to function as a cat. Still, we waited a bit longer, seeing the attempts to eat and drink as favorable signs. That night, twice, she walked directly over Baron, barely reacting when he growled and swatted at her except to pause and then begin walking forward again. We had to separate them, and we did our best to make the area she was in safe for her. Nonetheless, in the middle of the night, she got stuck in another corner underneath a set of shelves and ended up knocking over a planter filled with cactuses (she was luckily uninjured).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During all this time, we were in communication with the vet, who in the gentlest way possible had been repeatedly telling us that if Carbomb wasn&#39;t better by now, she was unlikely to get better. We discussed the possibility of the MRI, but even the vet thought it was a bad idea. The general anesthetic might kill a cat of that age and, truthfully, it didn&#39;t matter if it was a tumor or not – we weren&#39;t about to authorize brain surgery on a seventeen-year-old cat to find a potential tumor that, even if it existed and was removed, might not even improve her condition. It would be needlessly cruel to her to put her through that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Thursday morning, we called it. We were at the vet at 9 AM. By 10 AM, Carbomb was gone. We each held her for a time as they prepped (she fell asleep on both of us, again). Then they sedated her, and left her with us to fall asleep for a final time, and then we both held her while they gave her the shot that would stop her heart. I&#39;m not sorry we did it—I believe it was the right and merciful thing to do—but I will carry the memory of watching that injection with me for the rest of my life. In a way, I&#39;m lucky. I&#39;m 45 years old and this was the first pet I&#39;ve ever had to put down. It was, I think, the hardest thing I have so far ever had to do in my entire life. I am completely unashamed to say that I broke down sobbing first when we got into that little room that I knew was the last place I&#39;d see her alive, and again when the act was done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A little more background: I&#39;ve had a very difficult relationship with the cats. I am by nature more of a dog person – I want a pet, not a roommate. Cats are more of the latter. That said, I don&#39;t want a dog. They&#39;re too much work and too gross (I am also a pretty huge germaphobe, something I&#39;m working on). The cats, though, are also gross … something I wasn&#39;t prepared for when we adopted them - the amount of outside-the-litter-box puke, pee, and poop I&#39;ve had to deal with over the last decade and a half has been much, much higher than I anticipated. They also have strong personalities that sometimes clashed with mine - Carbomb in particular LOVED me so much that it was hard to deal with because if I interacted with her, she would get so amped up that she couldn&#39;t sit down, and then when she finally did, if I so much as shifted my legs, it would prompt another five minutes of circling. I was not sure, and remain unsure, that the cats were a net positive in my life, unless you include &amp;quot;made Charlotte happy&amp;quot; (which I do).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did/do like them. They have brought many moments of amusement to my life. It&#39;s made me happy that they like to hang out on the couch in my office when Charlotte&#39;s not home. I absolutely love watching Charlotte interact with them. Also, I liked them as individuals. They each have their own personality, and I appreciated aspects of each of theirs. Baron is the easier cat from a personality standpoint, but I liked a lot about Carbomb as well. There are plenty of good things about owning cats, but left to my own devices, I might not ever adopt another one. Charlotte is a wonderful cat owner. I am not. I&#39;m not a good enough cat owner, and was especially not a good enough cat owner to the one that loved me best. I ignored her desire for attention too often, and I was grumpy with her more than I should&#39;ve been. I was not a good enough cat owner. That fact haunts me, now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All that said, my view on pet adoption was that I&#39;d made a promise to these things that I would keep them as comfortable and content as I could, for as long as I could. Even when Carbomb went through a multi-year odyssey of semi-incontinence due to what ended up being a combination of factors (including a gluten allergy), I never seriously considered rehoming her. I wanted them to live long, happy lives &lt;em&gt;with us&lt;/em&gt;. That was the promise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Voluntarily telling a veterinarian to kill the pet I had shared sixteen years of my life with felt like a horrific betrayal of that promise. It still does. I know it was the right thing to do, but it doesn&#39;t change the way it feels, and the way it feels is terrible. But that&#39;s not really the worst of it. The worst of it is just the overwhelming fact that she is &lt;em&gt;not here&lt;/em&gt;. Every room I go into, there is some little reminder that Carbomb is &lt;em&gt;not here&lt;/em&gt; and is never going to be here again. She was in the world, and now she is not in the world, and she will never come back. I do not believe in a spirit, a soul, or an afterlife (I&#39;d love to, but I don&#39;t). I will not see my cat again. She is gone. And while I love her, and I hope I made it clear that I love her, especially in those last few days, it doesn&#39;t change anything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&#39;t have any good way to wrap up this post. I could write something pithy about how the beauty of these things is in their ephemerality, but I don&#39;t believe that. I don&#39;t agree with Kurzweil that without death, life is meaningless. I vehemently reject that notion. Carbomb mattered, and would have kept on mattering if she kept on living. That she matters in death, too, doesn&#39;t bring me any comfort. I&#39;d give a lot to put her on my lap again and let her circle for five stupid minutes while I roll my eyes and Charlotte laughs at me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s like I said: this isn&#39;t anything that anyone who&#39;s lost a pet hasn&#39;t experienced. It will go away in time. I&#39;ll remember her fondly, and with some sadness, but not this acute grief that I&#39;m currently feeling. I know that. I&#39;ll get through it. But right now, I miss my cat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I said elsewhere: she was special. They&#39;re all special.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://cwbwriting.com/_img/carbomb_memorial.jpg&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; style=&quot;width: 100%&quot; /&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>CWB Writing Newsletter - January 2023 | Post | CWB Writing</title>
    <link href="https://cwbwriting.com/posts/2023-01-cwb-writing-newsletter-january-2023/"/>
    <updated>2023-01-21T19:15:16Z</updated>
    <id>https://cwbwriting.com/posts/2023-01-cwb-writing-newsletter-january-2023/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s 2023!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wow, can you believe it? Somehow we got through another circle around the sun, and here we are again in a new year, facing the long dark of January and February. Fortunately, I&#39;ve got exciting news to share, so let&#39;s get to it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;New Book&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When last you heard from me (which was November, unless you&#39;re brand new to this newsletter), I&#39;d mentioned that I had a side project that was probably going to keep me away from writing for a bit. Well … that was put on hiatus, and I was absolutely dying to get started on the sequel to &lt;em&gt;Piety the Knife&lt;/em&gt;, so I got started on the sequel to &lt;em&gt;Piety the Knife&lt;/em&gt;). I&#39;m not going to tell you the name just yet, because it&#39;s a bit of a spoiler for the first book, but I&#39;ve been cranking away on it since December 12th.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s perhaps not a great idea to be writing this book. I still haven&#39;t landed an agent for &lt;em&gt;Piety&lt;/em&gt; and it makes basically zero sense to write a sequel to a book that hasn&#39;t even secured representation, much less been bought by a publisher. But sometimes you just gotta write what you want to write, whether it makes the most sense or not. I&#39;ve skipped writing sequels to a bunch of other books, many of which I would really love to write sequels for, because I was trying to get an agent, but in this case I think Piety might be my best work overall and I was too excited to keep writing stories in that world to just walk away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is probably frustrating for you. &amp;quot;Great, he&#39;s writing a sequel we can&#39;t read to a book we can&#39;t read&amp;quot; … yeah. That&#39;s not so hot. So here&#39;s the deal: I will make you two promises. The first is that if I fail to secure representation for this trilogy, I &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; eventually release it independently. You&#39;ll get to read Piety the Knife, its sequel, and the closing book in the trilogy someday. The other promise: if I don&#39;t have an agent by this summer, I will begin work on releasing &lt;em&gt;Possessed&lt;/em&gt; as an indie title.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&#39;t remember &lt;em&gt;Possessed&lt;/em&gt;? You can &lt;a href=&quot;https://cwbwriting.com/books/&quot;&gt;learn more about it on my writing site&lt;/a&gt;, but for a quick summary: it&#39;s a contemporary fantasy book in the style of Christopher Moore, featuring a lot of humor in addition to my trademarked (not actually trademarked) blend of action and character development. It&#39;s about a young woman living in the Miami suburbs who accidentally gets possessed by a demon. Do hijinks ensue? They absolutely do. Does she get into some dangerous situations? She absolutely does! Does she survive the end of the book? Well, I hope to give you a chance to find out!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, yeah … &lt;em&gt;Untitled Piety Sequel That&#39;s Not Actually Untitled&lt;/em&gt;? Going really well. I haven&#39;t missed a single day while writing it, I&#39;m almost to 70,000 words, and I&#39;m averaging an absurd 2,300 words a day. Not sure if I can keep up that pace or not, but I&#39;m having an absolute blast with it at the moment and am on track to finish it up sometime in early February, assuming it comes in around 120,000-130,000 words, which feels about right for the plans I have for the plot! That means by the March newsletter, it should be done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Piety the Knife&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not a ton new here to report. The book is out with the agent who requested significant revisions, now that I&#39;ve made those revisions. I&#39;m hoping like hell she likes what I&#39;ve done and is ready to take me on as a client. I think it&#39;s likely, but not guaranteed, I&#39;ll hear back from her before the March newsletter. Fingers crossed!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strike&gt;Book&lt;/strike&gt; Graphic Novel Recommendation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you haven&#39;t read &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.indiebound.org/book/9781632157096&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Monstress&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;http://marjoriemliu.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Majorie Liu&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://sanatakeda.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Sana Takeda&lt;/a&gt;, you are absolutely missing out. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.indiebound.org/book/9781632157096&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Grab volume one from your local indie bookstore&lt;/a&gt; (or, if you must, I guess keep lining Jeff Bezos&#39;s pockets and use Amazon, but seriously … go indie)! You will not regret it, I promise you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Catch you in March!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;-Chris&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;You can get these updates before they hit the blog by subscribing to the newsletter!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>An Explanation of My Issues With AI-Generated Images | Post | CWB Writing</title>
    <link href="https://cwbwriting.com/posts/2022-12-on-ai-art/"/>
    <updated>2023-01-21T19:06:58Z</updated>
    <id>https://cwbwriting.com/posts/2022-12-on-ai-art/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The last few months have seen an explosion of AI-generated images, both those that are photorealistic and those that emulate various illustrators. There are a swarm of questions surrounding these images, so I thought I&#39;d tackle a few of those and then talk at slightly more length about why my opinion is what it is. So … the questions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Q. Is AI-generate imagery ethical?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
A. Not in its current form, no.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Q. Isn&#39;t AI-generated imagery the same as an artist who learns by studying, copying, and ultimately absorbing the work of others?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
A. Not in its current form, no.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Q. Is AI-generated imagery &amp;quot;Art?&amp;quot;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
A. Not in its current form, no. Also, who cares, because &amp;quot;what is art?&amp;quot; is among the most pointless, futile, and ultimately worthless questions one can ask. But if we must ask it, then going by not just my definition of &amp;quot;art&amp;quot; but any vaguely societally accepted definition of &amp;quot;art,&amp;quot; I repeat … not in its current form, no.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which begs a final question:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Q. Can AI-generated imagery BE &amp;quot;art?&amp;quot;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
A. Yes, absolutely, without question. It will get there, but it will not get there as fast as people think it will get there for one reason, and that reason is a single word, around which I&#39;m going to frame the entire rest of this post. That word is: &amp;quot;intent.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first thing we need to clear up is that &amp;quot;AI&amp;quot; images are not made by AI. They are made by Machine Learning, which is the very early stages of a technology that may someday yield something like AI. Artificial Intelligence, which of course is what AI stands for, is still quite a ways off. Machine Learning is not an intelligence. It&#39;s a set of algorithms that can be given a task and, through a combination of training and model adjustments, can improve at that task over time. It&#39;s one of many building blocks that will be needed for true AI, but it&#39;s not AI. Machine Learning algorithms do not think. They cannot set their own goals, and what progress they make is limited to fairly straightforward trial and error, the results of which need to be validated by human beings (or validated against goals established by human beings, such as &amp;quot;finish this Mario level without dying&amp;quot;). So, for the rest of this post, we&#39;ll be replacing the &amp;quot;AI&amp;quot; acronym with the much more accurate &amp;quot;ML.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we understand the difference between what we have (ML) and what will someday exist (AI), we can also understand where &amp;quot;intent&amp;quot; comes in pretty rapidly, I think. Machine Learning does not have intent when it makes art. One can argue that the &amp;quot;intent&amp;quot; is supplied by the human who provides the prompts to the ML image generator, but I think this is pretty facile. It&#39;s honestly amusing to see people on the internet bickering over prompt ownership, as if coming up with something like &amp;quot;Sexy fair-skinned lady with dragon horns and green eyes in the style of &lt;a href=&quot;https://rossdraws.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Ross Draws&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot; is a difficult creative exercise. The &amp;quot;intent&amp;quot; here is not to produce a unique work of art through the culmination of one&#39;s experience, practice, training, skill, and (yes, for sure, for every human artist who has lived at least since first our ancestors scraped pictures of mammoths into cave walls) one&#39;s influences. The &amp;quot;intent&amp;quot; is to try and talk a machine into producing something that one finds visually pleasing - the machine itself has no intent beyond fulfilling the requirements of its programming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A common argument I&#39;ve seen in favor of ML-generated imagery as &amp;quot;art&amp;quot; is that human artists&#39; works are really no more than the sum of their influences, the same as a computer that&#39;s been trained on hundreds or thousands of images by various artists. Let&#39;s leave aside the ethics involved in taking an artist&#39;s work without their permission and using it to train a Machine Learning model, because those ethics are &lt;em&gt;spectacularly&lt;/em&gt; grim and have very little to do with a human artist sitting in a museum and making a reference drawing of an old masterwork (the closest analog I&#39;ve seen anyone come up with). Let&#39;s instead consider just the actual mechanics of this training, for both human beings and computers. Let&#39;s consider the claim that there&#39;s no difference between what the human is doing and what the machine is doing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Human artists are unquestionably influenced by other artists, and arguing otherwise is a fool&#39;s game. Many of history&#39;s greatest masters spent years, if not decades, directly copying the work of older masters. All of the modern age&#39;s crop of incredible illustrators—folks like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tommyarnoldart.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Tommy Arnold&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.karlaortizart.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Karla Ortiz&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/pepelarraz/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Pepe Larraz&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://sanatakeda.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Sana Takeda&lt;/a&gt; or a thousand other amazing artists—owe a great deal to their artistic influences. The people whose work they looked at that made them think &amp;quot;I want to draw/paint/etc like that.&amp;quot; This is not in doubt, and with any of these artists it&#39;s a guarantee that to this day, no matter how their personal styles have evolved, you can see the ghosts of those influences within them. So … what&#39;s the difference? The difference is intent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me put it this way: when I go to draw a nose, sometimes I draw a nose that looks like a nose that an artist I like drew. Not &lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;/em&gt; like it, probably, in part because I don&#39;t have as much training or practice or skill as the artists I look up to, but close enough for government work. In this instance, what I&#39;m doing is very similar to the way Machine Learning operates. I&#39;m recalling (or looking directly at) how other artists have solved the problem of representing a human nose, and doing my best to impersonate that. While I am indeed operating with intent here, that intent being &amp;quot;I want to draw the nose in the cool way this other person does,&amp;quot; that intent at least resembles the operation of the ML algorithm, even if such an algorithm isn&#39;t really operating with that same intent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But that&#39;s not the only way I draw a nose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, what I do instead is draw the skull first. Then I layer the actual anatomy of the nose on top of that. The skull provides the nasal bones, and the rest is cartilage – the upper laterals, the nasal septal, the lateral crus, etc. Then there&#39;s flesh on top of that, which requires erasing a lot of the subsurface lines while still preserving the shapes that they generate in the flesh layed on top of them. I do this with intent: to understand the &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; of drawing a nose. I do this to understand and solve the problem of representing this form in a way that will read as both anatomically correct and visually appealing to human eyes (within the scope of the drawing&#39;s style - manga faces are in no way anatomically correct but they &lt;em&gt;read&lt;/em&gt; as correct, and visually appealing to many people, within the style of the art). I do this to establish muscle and visual memory that will allow me to solve this problem more reliably without having to take the intermediate steps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, I don&#39;t draw all of the underlying substructure, but neither do I draw a nose that comes from my personal memory bank. Sometimes I experiment with form, line weight, angle, shading … a dozen other variables. Sometimes I do this while looking at reference. Sometimes I do it from my own imagination. It&#39;s this exercise, in the long run, that truly establishes an artists&#39; style. It&#39;s the reason you can look at any piece of &lt;a href=&quot;https://loish.net/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Loish&lt;/a&gt; artwork and know, immediately, that it&#39;s hers – even while being able to see the influence of things like the Disney movies of the 90s clearly shining through. She is an amalgamation of her influences, but she is also something uniquely her own, because of the many millions of lines she&#39;s laid down over the course of years of practicing. Of drawing with intent. Loish&#39;s art is not, to simplify things absurdly for the sake of clarity, &amp;quot;Disney + Manga + Alfonse Mucha = Loish&amp;quot; but rather &amp;quot;Disney + Manga + Alfonse Mucha + &lt;strong&gt;Loish&lt;/strong&gt; = Loish.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Machine Learning-generated images are often beautiful. They&#39;re also often distinguishable from the artists on whose work they were trained, albeit usually because there is something uncanny or not-quite-right about them compared to work that was made with intent. Nonetheless, ML-generated images can be claimed to have a style that is their own, even if that style&#39;s influences are worn on its sleeve. I maintain that there is a significant difference between a style obtained solely by mashing together bits of data, and a style obtained by acting with intent, and I believe its at the core of the latter where &amp;quot;art&amp;quot; is typically found.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The machines will get there. They&#39;re going to get a lot of places, some of them very soon, some of them a little later, but they&#39;ll get there. It&#39;s going to be scary for most people, at some point. Your job, whatever your job is, will be threatened first by Machine Learning and then, later, by true artificial intelligence. My job as a software engineer, my writing, my illustration (amateur though it is) — all of these are already threatened by Machine Learning. I can&#39;t control that. What I can control is the work I choose to consume - what I look at, what I support, what I pay for. When the machines can deliver art made with intent, if I am still alive when they get there, I will reevaluate. For now, they cannot. I&#39;m sticking with human beings.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>CWB Writing Newsletter - November 2022 | Post | CWB Writing</title>
    <link href="https://cwbwriting.com/posts/cwb-writing-newsletter-november-2022/"/>
    <updated>2023-01-21T19:06:58Z</updated>
    <id>https://cwbwriting.com/posts/cwb-writing-newsletter-november-2022/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hi There!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s been another couple of months, so let&#39;s catch up, shall we?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Piety the Knife&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When last we spoke, I was about to embark upon the third draft of &lt;em&gt;Piety the Knife&lt;/em&gt;, my latest manuscript, at the request of an agent who&#39;s interested in representing me but didn&#39;t think the book was quite &lt;em&gt;there&lt;/em&gt; yet. Well, I&#39;m pleased to say that the time since the last newsletter has been immensely productive, and the third draft of Piety the Knife is now finished. I honestly thought the second draft was really strong (and it seems agents agreed - it got the most attention of any book I&#39;ve ever written that didn&#39;t end up with offers of representation), but I think this one&#39;s even better. It solidifies a lot of things, gives further depth to the various characters, adjusts the pacing in several positive ways, and in general tells Piety&#39;s story in a way that I think (hope) is super-compelling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Will it land me an agent? I have no idea! This business is crazy, and it&#39;s particularly crazy right now, because the industry got all backed up due to COVID, so now publishers are taking on fewer books, which means agents are signing fewer authors. Nonetheless, I remain optimistic. I think this is a &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; good book, and I hope I&#39;ll someday be able to get it into your hands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reminder: New Website&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As mentioned in the last newsletter, I finally did something with &lt;a href=&quot;https://cwbwriting.com/&quot;&gt;CWBWriting.com&lt;/a&gt;. You can find all of my writing there, of course, but there&#39;s also a blog which I do occasionally update, and not only with these newsletters. My last post was some musing on Facebook&#39;s myriad failings. How can you possibly not want to check out content like &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt;?!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, you should totally check it out. It&#39;s cool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Book Recommendation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really, really liked &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.indiebound.org/book/9781250854117&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Nona the Ninth&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, probably even more than I liked &lt;em&gt;Gideon the Ninth&lt;/em&gt; and definitely more than I liked &lt;em&gt;Harrow the Ninth&lt;/em&gt; (which I still liked, don&#39;t get me wrong!). If you haven&#39;t read any of the Locked Tomb series by Tamsyn Muir, I definitely recommend them. If you&#39;ve read Gideon and Harrow but haven&#39;t gotten to Nona yet … get to Nona!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Brief Hiatus&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So … I am weirdly actually itching to write something new right now (preferably the sequel to Piety but that would be getting ahead of myself). Unfortunately, I have some contract work I need to do in the evenings and on weekends, so I may have to take a short time off from writing. Like a month or two. That doesn&#39;t mean there won&#39;t be a newsletter in January, though. Hopefully by then I&#39;ll have heard from the agent who&#39;s interested in Piety and, if I&#39;m lucky, it&#39;ll be good news.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If not? Well, I have some other things up my sleeve. Mostly doves, though. And maybe a rabbit. Or one of those handkerchief chains that just keeps on going and going. But also some things related to writing. Stick around. Whatever happens, you&#39;ll be the first to hear!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until next time!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;-Chris&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;You can get these updates before they hit the blog by subscribing to the newsletter!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>On Facebook | Post | CWB Writing</title>
    <link href="https://cwbwriting.com/posts/2022-10-on-facebook/"/>
    <updated>2023-01-21T19:06:58Z</updated>
    <id>https://cwbwriting.com/posts/2022-10-on-facebook/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In light of recent reports that Facebook is bleeding both users and revenue, I want to talk about the site and its slow slide into irrelevance, and why I believe the 2010s focus on “Engagement” as the most important metric for measuring site performance is responsible for that slide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Engagement,” for those who don’t know, is measured by tracking EVERYTHING A USER DOES on a site and measuring which activities keep them on the page longer. Literally every single time you click, and probably even mouse over things on Facebook, you’re being measured.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When people talk about “The Algorithm” what they mean is actually a bunch of algorithms, which are just chunks of code that behave in certain ways. “The Algorithm” is code that looks at what content spikes “Engagement” and attempts to put that content in front of users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is also a non-algorithmic aspect to hunting for “Engagement” – the entire company, whether it’s coders, content creators, marketers, whatever, become focused on building a site that generates “Engagement.” The reason for this is really very simple, and even make sense: The longer you keep users interacting with the site, the more ads they see and the more data on them you collect. Showing ads and selling your data to other companies is how Facebook makes money. So, from a purely profit-driven standpoint, courting “Engagement” makes sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have you seen the problem yet? It’s also pretty straightforward: “Engagement” is not the same thing as “Enjoyment.” This is something I’ve been harping on for years, because I believe that pursuing the former at the expense of the latter is a long-term problem. I also believe we’ve been seeing that problem blooming like a grotesque flower over at Facebook since well before the disastrous 2016 election.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A curious trick of our brains is that we will engage with a LOT of content that ACTIVELY MAKES US UNHAPPY. Facebook courts this. Not because they want unhappy users, but because they don’t care. They want “Engaged” users, and what’s more engaging than fighting with people over the internet? Not much, except maybe participating in echo chambers that reaffirm our most deeply-held beliefs (another service Facebook happily provides).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, people were spending more and more time on Facebook, but becoming unhappier and unhappier while doing so. This leads to a short-term spike in “Engagement,” but in the long term it undermines people’s desire to remain a part of the site. And, EVEN MORE IMPORTANTLY, it leads to new people not wanting to join the site, because all they hear is how awful it is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, because Facebook has focused all of this time on “Engagement” at the expense of “Enjoyment”, there is now an entire generation of internet users who hear “Facebook” and think: “That’s the place where all the old people hang out and yell at each other and are miserable.” Not exactly a ringing endorsement. Combine that with a Silicon-Valley-Libertarian ethos that refuses to do anything about right wing cesspools on the site, and you get … well, you get what Facebook is getting: a diminishing userbase as people leave the site and new users don’t come along.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, is this the ONLY reason for Facebook’s troubles? No, certainly not, but I believe it’s a significant reason, and a strong cautionary tale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s it for this one. Thanks for sticking with me, if you did!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>CWB Writing Newsletter - September 2022 | Post | CWB Writing</title>
    <link href="https://cwbwriting.com/posts/cwb-writing-newsletter-september-2022/"/>
    <updated>2023-01-21T19:06:58Z</updated>
    <id>https://cwbwriting.com/posts/cwb-writing-newsletter-september-2022/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m back!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sorry for the missing the July update. It turns out when you lose your job with five days&#39; notice (and three of those are a long weekend), you kind of go into scramble mode, and your hobbies and/or semi-professional work have to go on hold while you look for, find, interview for, accept, and start at a new job. Especially when you add a preexisting trip to France, getting COVID for the first time after two and a half years, and being the Best Man in a wedding into the mix!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I&#39;ve been busy. Which means a short update this month … but that&#39;s okay! Let&#39;s jump in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Unending Agent Search&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I talked extensively about the agent search and how it works in the last newsletter. Not gonna rehash that here, but I will go over the major thing happening right now: I&#39;ve had an agent request revisions on my latest book, Piety the Knife. I meant to make them over the last two or three months but, well, the first paragraph of this email happened!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But now I&#39;m a bit more back in the saddle. I&#39;m once again going over all of the notes (the agent&#39;s and my own) and preparing to take a stab at a third draft of the book. I have no idea how long it&#39;s going to take me to round it into shape, and I have a lot of other stuff going on in my life right now, but with summer winding down I&#39;m hoping to find enough time to hack away at it. So, let&#39;s see where we are in two months. Hopefully much further along than reading notes!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m also kicking around ideas for two new books, because of course I am. One of them would be straight historical fiction with no fantasy elements (or very minor ones). The other would be a horror story but with a pretty significant twist that I don&#39;t want to discuss just yet. I&#39;m still figuring out how it would work! Probably won&#39;t get to either of those this year, but they&#39;ve definitely been rolling around in my brain while I run, or shower, or am doing stuff like mowing the lawn, which is how my books always start.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;New Websiii-heee-iiitte&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After literally years of owning CWBWriting.com, I finally put a website up there! It includes information on all of my books and stories, an occasionally-updated blog, some stuff about me, and so forth. Also it has a light and dark mode and will remember your preference, because what kind of web developer would I be if I didn&#39;t offer dark mode in 2022?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Swing by! Check it out! Maybe subscribe to the RSS feed in case I ever post anything there that&#39;s not just a duplicate of this newsletter! Exclamation points!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And … that&#39;s really about it for this month. See you in November!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;-Chris&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;You can get these updates before they hit the blog by subscribing to the newsletter!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Welcome to CWB Writing | Post | CWB Writing</title>
    <link href="https://cwbwriting.com/posts/welcome-to-cwb-writing/"/>
    <updated>2023-01-21T19:06:58Z</updated>
    <id>https://cwbwriting.com/posts/welcome-to-cwb-writing/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;h3&gt;Welcome to CWB Writing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hi there,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After many failed attempts to get this site off the ground, I&#39;ve finally found the time and energy to get this site off the ground! I felt it was time that my writing had its own dedicated spot on the web, rather than existing as a tab on my personal site alongside such exciting information as what basketball team I like to root for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that in mind, I intend to update this site semi-regularly with writing news, thoughts, tips, info, etc. At the very least, it&#39;ll get updated every couple of months when I post my bi-monthly writing newsletter, though I should point out that you&#39;ll get these at least a week early if you subscribe using the box that is either to your right (on larger screens) or down below (on phones and such).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently I&#39;m working on some requested revisions to &lt;em&gt;Piety the Knife&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https://cwbwriting.com/posts/cwb-writing-newsletter-may-2022/&quot;&gt;see this update&lt;/a&gt;) and starting to think about my next story. Right now I&#39;m kicking around a couple of ideas, one of which is the story of someone who isn&#39;t the CHOSEN ONE but hangs out with the CHOSEN ONE, and one of which is about the Late Bronze Age collapse and the mysterious &amp;quot;Sea People&amp;quot; who may&#39;ve caused it. Maybe I&#39;ll merge those two into one thing. Or maybe I&#39;ll write something else entirely. You never know until you start putting words on digital paper!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>CWB Writing Newsletter - May 2022 | Post | CWB Writing</title>
    <link href="https://cwbwriting.com/posts/cwb-writing-newsletter-may-2022/"/>
    <updated>2023-01-21T19:06:58Z</updated>
    <id>https://cwbwriting.com/posts/cwb-writing-newsletter-may-2022/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hello There!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What an interesting couple of months it&#39;s been. I don&#39;t have &lt;em&gt;great&lt;/em&gt; news, but I do have &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; news, which is … well, not bad! Let&#39;s get to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Unending Agent Search&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s talk about the agent hunt. For those new to this newsletter or who&#39;ve forgotten how this goes, it works like this: I send out &amp;quot;queries&amp;quot; which are single page descriptions of the new book, usually along with some information about yourself. Most (but not all) agents also ask you to send a small sample of the book, ranging from the first five pages to the first three chapters. MOST queries end up in rejections (or &amp;quot;closed, no response&amp;quot; because some agents only respond when they want more). I follow a lot of agents on Twitter and many of them get over 1,000 queries in a given month. Ambitious agents might take on six or seven authors in a given &lt;em&gt;year&lt;/em&gt;. The odds are always against the author.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the agent is interested, they will generally ask for a &amp;quot;partial&amp;quot; (more of the book but not the whole thing) or a &amp;quot;full&amp;quot; (the full manuscript). An agent who asked for a partial will either reject or, if interested, upgrade to a full. Once an agent has read the full, one of three things will happen: they will either pass on representing the work, they will ask for revisions, or they will offer representation. The latter is the goal, though it only represents one more step on a very long journey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SO … with all that in mind, let&#39;s talk numbers. I have sent out a whopping &lt;em&gt;seventy&lt;/em&gt; queries for my latest book, Piety the Knife, a dark fantasy novel. Of those queries, so far thirty-six have resulted in rejections with no page requests, and two in &amp;quot;closed, no response.&amp;quot; That cuts us down to thirty-two. Of which, 26 are still outstanding. That means six agents have so far requested at least a partial manuscript (in fact, I got five full requests and one partial).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None of those six have offered representation. One rejected on the partial. Three others rejected on the full. One is still outstanding but is probably a reject at this point. The final agent has requested revisions, but does believe that if I can get the story to where she thinks it needs to be to sell it, she would like to represent it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Believe it or not, this is a very good result. It&#39;s actually a spectacular result. Six requests for pages is the most I&#39;ve ever gotten on any book I&#39;ve ever queried, including Elixir, the novel that landed me my first agent. &lt;em&gt;All&lt;/em&gt; of the agents who rejected after requesting the full sent personalized feedback saying they thought I was a talented writer and to make sure I query them with my next book if I&#39;m still seeking representation. That&#39;s a really good sign.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the &amp;quot;revise and resubmit&amp;quot; (R&amp;amp;R) is the best sign of the bunch. This gives me an actual target. &amp;quot;If you can do what&#39;s needed, you will likely get an agent.&amp;quot; I spent over two hours on Zoom with the agent in question, and I&#39;m extremely confident that a) she&#39;s well read in the genres I write, b) she&#39;s very passionate about the genres I write, and c) she would be an excellent champion for the book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now: the hard part. Rewrites. I&#39;ve spent the past couple of weeks working on a plan to get the book into shape, taking into account her feedback, her assistant&#39;s feedback, my wife&#39;s thoughts, and my own gut instincts. I&#39;m just about ready to begin chopping, adding, and changing. I don&#39;t expect the process to be lengthy, but I &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; expect it to be difficult. Writing is hard work. But this is as close as I&#39;ve been in a while to finding representation for my books, and the goal remains the same: get an agent, get a book sold to publishers, get that book on the shelves. I&#39;ve wanted it since I was eleven years old. Gonna keep pursuing it till it happens, or I&#39;m dead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#39;s all I&#39;ve got this month. See you in July, hopefully with good news!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;-Chris&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;You can get these updates before they hit the blog by subscribing to the newsletter!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
