<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>CWB Writing</title>
  <subtitle>The Works of Christopher Buecheler</subtitle>
  <link href="https://cwbwriting.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://cwbwriting.com/"/>
  <updated>2022-10-02T12:42:36Z</updated>
  <id>https://cwbwriting.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name>Christopher Buecheler</name>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  
  <entry>
    <title>On Facebook | Post | CWB Writing</title>
    <link href="https://cwbwriting.com/posts/2022-10-on-facebook/"/>
    <updated>2022-10-02T12:42:36Z</updated>
    <id>https://cwbwriting.com/posts/2022-10-on-facebook/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post is adapted from a series of tweets I made the other day. If musings like these interest you, maybe consider &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/cwbuecheler/&quot;&gt;following me on Twitter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In light of recent reports that Facebook is bleeding both users and revenue, I want to talk about the site and its slow slide into irrelevance, and why I believe the 2010s focus on “Engagement” as the most important metric for measuring site performance is responsible for that slide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Engagement,” for those who don’t know, is measured by tracking EVERYTHING A USER DOES on a site and measuring which activities keep them on the page longer. Literally every single time you click, and probably even mouse over things on Facebook, you’re being measured.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When people talk about “The Algorithm” what they mean is actually a bunch of algorithms, which are just chunks of code that behave in certain ways. “The Algorithm” is code that looks at what content spikes “Engagement” and attempts to put that content in front of users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is also a non-algorithmic aspect to hunting for “Engagement” – the entire company, whether it’s coders, content creators, marketers, whatever, become focused on building a site that generates “Engagement.” The reason for this is really very simple, and even make sense: The longer you keep users interacting with the site, the more ads they see and the more data on them you collect. Showing ads and selling your data to other companies is how Facebook makes money. So, from a purely profit-driven standpoint, courting “Engagement” makes sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have you seen the problem yet? It’s also pretty straightforward: “Engagement” is not the same thing as “Enjoyment.” This is something I’ve been harping on for years, because I believe that pursuing the former at the expense of the latter is a long-term problem. I also believe we’ve been seeing that problem blooming like a grotesque flower over at Facebook since well before the disastrous 2016 election.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A curious trick of our brains is that we will engage with a LOT of content that ACTIVELY MAKES US UNHAPPY. Facebook courts this. Not because they want unhappy users, but because they don’t care. They want “Engaged” users, and what’s more engaging than fighting with people over the internet? Not much, except maybe participating in echo chambers that reaffirm our most deeply-held beliefs (another service Facebook happily provides).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, people were spending more and more time on Facebook, but becoming unhappier and unhappier while doing so. This leads to a short-term spike in “Engagement,” but in the long term it undermines people’s desire to remain a part of the site. And, EVEN MORE IMPORTANTLY, it leads to new people not wanting to join the site, because all they hear is how awful it is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, because Facebook has focused all of this time on “Engagement” at the expense of “Enjoyment”, there is now an entire generation of internet users who hear “Facebook” and think: “That’s the place where all the old people hang out and yell at each other and are miserable.” Not exactly a ringing endorsement. Combine that with a Silicon-Valley-Libertarian ethos that refuses to do anything about right wing cesspools on the site, and you get … well, you get what Facebook is getting: a diminishing userbase as people leave the site and new users don’t come along.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, is this the ONLY reason for Facebook’s troubles? No, certainly not, but I believe it’s a significant reason, and a strong cautionary tale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s it for this one. Thanks for sticking with me, if you did!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>CWB Writing Newsletter - September 2022 | Post | CWB Writing</title>
    <link href="https://cwbwriting.com/posts/cwb-writing-newsletter-september-2022/"/>
    <updated>2022-10-02T12:39:55Z</updated>
    <id>https://cwbwriting.com/posts/cwb-writing-newsletter-september-2022/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m back!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sorry for the missing the July update. It turns out when you lose your job with five days&#39; notice (and three of those are a long weekend), you kind of go into scramble mode, and your hobbies and/or semi-professional work have to go on hold while you look for, find, interview for, accept, and start at a new job. Especially when you add a preexisting trip to France, getting COVID for the first time after two and a half years, and being the Best Man in a wedding into the mix!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I&#39;ve been busy. Which means a short update this month … but that&#39;s okay! Let&#39;s jump in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Unending Agent Search&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I talked extensively about the agent search and how it works in the last newsletter. Not gonna rehash that here, but I will go over the major thing happening right now: I&#39;ve had an agent request revisions on my latest book, Piety the Knife. I meant to make them over the last two or three months but, well, the first paragraph of this email happened!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But now I&#39;m a bit more back in the saddle. I&#39;m once again going over all of the notes (the agent&#39;s and my own) and preparing to take a stab at a third draft of the book. I have no idea how long it&#39;s going to take me to round it into shape, and I have a lot of other stuff going on in my life right now, but with summer winding down I&#39;m hoping to find enough time to hack away at it. So, let&#39;s see where we are in two months. Hopefully much further along than reading notes!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m also kicking around ideas for two new books, because of course I am. One of them would be straight historical fiction with no fantasy elements (or very minor ones). The other would be a horror story but with a pretty significant twist that I don&#39;t want to discuss just yet. I&#39;m still figuring out how it would work! Probably won&#39;t get to either of those this year, but they&#39;ve definitely been rolling around in my brain while I run, or shower, or am doing stuff like mowing the lawn, which is how my books always start.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;New Websiii-heee-iiitte&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After literally years of owning CWBWriting.com, I finally put a website up there! It includes information on all of my books and stories, an occasionally-updated blog, some stuff about me, and so forth. Also it has a light and dark mode and will remember your preference, because what kind of web developer would I be if I didn&#39;t offer dark mode in 2022?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Swing by! Check it out! Maybe subscribe to the RSS feed in case I ever post anything there that&#39;s not just a duplicate of this newsletter! Exclamation points!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And … that&#39;s really about it for this month. See you in November!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;-Chris&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;You can get these updates before they hit the blog by subscribing to the newsletter!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Welcome to CWB Writing | Post | CWB Writing</title>
    <link href="https://cwbwriting.com/posts/welcome-to-cwb-writing/"/>
    <updated>2022-10-02T12:39:55Z</updated>
    <id>https://cwbwriting.com/posts/welcome-to-cwb-writing/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;h3&gt;Welcome to CWB Writing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hi there,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After many failed attempts to get this site off the ground, I&#39;ve finally found the time and energy to get this site off the ground! I felt it was time that my writing had its own dedicated spot on the web, rather than existing as a tab on my personal site alongside such exciting information as what basketball team I like to root for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that in mind, I intend to update this site semi-regularly with writing news, thoughts, tips, info, etc. At the very least, it&#39;ll get updated every couple of months when I post my bi-monthly writing newsletter, though I should point out that you&#39;ll get these at least a week early if you subscribe using the box that is either to your right (on larger screens) or down below (on phones and such).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently I&#39;m working on some requested revisions to &lt;em&gt;Piety the Knife&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https://cwbwriting.com/posts/cwb-writing-newsletter-may-2022/&quot;&gt;see this update&lt;/a&gt;) and starting to think about my next story. Right now I&#39;m kicking around a couple of ideas, one of which is the story of someone who isn&#39;t the CHOSEN ONE but hangs out with the CHOSEN ONE, and one of which is about the Late Bronze Age collapse and the mysterious &amp;quot;Sea People&amp;quot; who may&#39;ve caused it. Maybe I&#39;ll merge those two into one thing. Or maybe I&#39;ll write something else entirely. You never know until you start putting words on digital paper!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>CWB Writing Newsletter - May 2022 | Post | CWB Writing</title>
    <link href="https://cwbwriting.com/posts/cwb-writing-newsletter-may-2022/"/>
    <updated>2022-10-02T12:39:55Z</updated>
    <id>https://cwbwriting.com/posts/cwb-writing-newsletter-may-2022/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hello There!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What an interesting couple of months it&#39;s been. I don&#39;t have &lt;em&gt;great&lt;/em&gt; news, but I do have &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; news, which is … well, not bad! Let&#39;s get to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Unending Agent Search&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s talk about the agent hunt. For those new to this newsletter or who&#39;ve forgotten how this goes, it works like this: I send out &amp;quot;queries&amp;quot; which are single page descriptions of the new book, usually along with some information about yourself. Most (but not all) agents also ask you to send a small sample of the book, ranging from the first five pages to the first three chapters. MOST queries end up in rejections (or &amp;quot;closed, no response&amp;quot; because some agents only respond when they want more). I follow a lot of agents on Twitter and many of them get over 1,000 queries in a given month. Ambitious agents might take on six or seven authors in a given &lt;em&gt;year&lt;/em&gt;. The odds are always against the author.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the agent is interested, they will generally ask for a &amp;quot;partial&amp;quot; (more of the book but not the whole thing) or a &amp;quot;full&amp;quot; (the full manuscript). An agent who asked for a partial will either reject or, if interested, upgrade to a full. Once an agent has read the full, one of three things will happen: they will either pass on representing the work, they will ask for revisions, or they will offer representation. The latter is the goal, though it only represents one more step on a very long journey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SO … with all that in mind, let&#39;s talk numbers. I have sent out a whopping &lt;em&gt;seventy&lt;/em&gt; queries for my latest book, Piety the Knife, a dark fantasy novel. Of those queries, so far thirty-six have resulted in rejections with no page requests, and two in &amp;quot;closed, no response.&amp;quot; That cuts us down to thirty-two. Of which, 26 are still outstanding. That means six agents have so far requested at least a partial manuscript (in fact, I got five full requests and one partial).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None of those six have offered representation. One rejected on the partial. Three others rejected on the full. One is still outstanding but is probably a reject at this point. The final agent has requested revisions, but does believe that if I can get the story to where she thinks it needs to be to sell it, she would like to represent it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Believe it or not, this is a very good result. It&#39;s actually a spectacular result. Six requests for pages is the most I&#39;ve ever gotten on any book I&#39;ve ever queried, including Elixir, the novel that landed me my first agent. &lt;em&gt;All&lt;/em&gt; of the agents who rejected after requesting the full sent personalized feedback saying they thought I was a talented writer and to make sure I query them with my next book if I&#39;m still seeking representation. That&#39;s a really good sign.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the &amp;quot;revise and resubmit&amp;quot; (R&amp;amp;R) is the best sign of the bunch. This gives me an actual target. &amp;quot;If you can do what&#39;s needed, you will likely get an agent.&amp;quot; I spent over two hours on Zoom with the agent in question, and I&#39;m extremely confident that a) she&#39;s well read in the genres I write, b) she&#39;s very passionate about the genres I write, and c) she would be an excellent champion for the book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now: the hard part. Rewrites. I&#39;ve spent the past couple of weeks working on a plan to get the book into shape, taking into account her feedback, her assistant&#39;s feedback, my wife&#39;s thoughts, and my own gut instincts. I&#39;m just about ready to begin chopping, adding, and changing. I don&#39;t expect the process to be lengthy, but I &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; expect it to be difficult. Writing is hard work. But this is as close as I&#39;ve been in a while to finding representation for my books, and the goal remains the same: get an agent, get a book sold to publishers, get that book on the shelves. I&#39;ve wanted it since I was eleven years old. Gonna keep pursuing it till it happens, or I&#39;m dead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#39;s all I&#39;ve got this month. See you in July, hopefully with good news!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;-Chris&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;You can get these updates before they hit the blog by subscribing to the newsletter!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
